[Music]
h
how
[Music]
o
w
[Music]
[Applause]
oh
[Music]
o oh
we're gonna open up with
pray welcome living Mana online church
family welcome to the last Sabbath
school and divine service of 202
for amen amen for those who may be
tuning in for the first time and don't
know us let us introduce ourselves
really quickly my name is Amar soell and
this is Terry soell he is the director
of our prayer ministry here at Living
Mana church and we are so blessed to be
here as you can see Pastor Ivor and at
tante are not here they are visiting
family and we send our love and prayers
to you
and uh just grateful for everything that
you do here for living Mana church
amen so where is everyone tuning in from
please put in the chat where you are uh
tuning in from and if this is your very
first time at Living Mana Church please
put a one in the chat so that we can
greet you amen amen well we're going to
start right off out of South Carolina
with sister Ashley Owens sister Ashley
you from my home state all right
Hallelujah hi
blessing Ayana amen greetings Bernice
bringham is here greetings everyone
they'll start coming up in a moment
y'all y'all know not to do too much with
me now because I I'll start a roll call
but that's for later all right but we
just want to call later yes we want to
give you a shout out where you where you
watching from yes yes yes here we come
Robert it is so Well with My Soul well
thank you hallelujah hallelujah brother
Texas yes Sheila from New
Jersey ayyan from Trinidad and Tobago
yes Hallelujah Barbara Simmons from
anguila oh our beloved sister Sheila is
here from New Jersey Terence from New
York City hello and welcome our sister
Haddie from Long Beach California is
here John Mayor from Dylan South
Carolina wait a minute all my folks in
the house today South Carolina
representing today love y'all family
Hallelujah and from Colorado we have
Christina my beloved sister love you
Christina Janice Ferguson from bise
welcome Janice so good to see you amen
just a reminder that here at Living Mana
um we are a fully virtual church so um
but we are one of the most active
churches I've ever been in absolutely it
has been just a blessing here at Living
Mana with all the fellowship and the
weekly programming we have things
happening every day Mondays we have
mental health Mondays with the tante and
Dr Ricardo white we're on a very short
holiday break but we will be back soon
and then Tuesdays we have true Health
Tuesdays uh coming back soon with a new
uh guest Maria hmel who's a
licensed uh nutritionist and she travels
around and speaks about nutrition and
diet so we're looking forward to having
her with us on Tuesdays definitely of
course Wednesdays is power Wednesdays
amen with theay
team if you have never experienced power
Wednesday please come amen we share
either a short devotional or we have
testimonies and we really pray it is an
amazing time of Fellowship an amazing
time of testimonies and faith and um
just sharing just sharing prayers and
praises to the Lord amen and and you
know uh just as a brief plug for the
prayer team I can't say enough about the
prayer team and the prayer warriors you
know uh I am humble to be able to be a
servant leader amongst these beautiful
brothers and sisters and I'm gonna tell
you something it's just a constant
blessing so if you if you can't get
enough of living Mana in your small
group or Mighty networks or in the in
the weekly programming get on one of
these special ops prayer teams they'll
keep you up all night believe me and uh
we we have such a time in the Lord we're
growing and just moving forward so
Thursdays yes Lami Richardson is having
a testimony uh Thursdays which is
amazing um and I actually watched one of
them on YouTube and it was truly a
blessing and then Fridays we have a
traditional Sabbath Bible study so
there's something happening at Living
Mana almost every night I believe
Sundays are the only night that we don't
do something but we're always praying so
there's is something happening and just
to back up a minute let's just sweep
back over Thursday and Friday real quick
Thursday something new is coming with
Pastor Lami we'll tell you about that
during the announcements later you don't
want to miss that that's G to be really
exciting um but on Fridays yeah I mean I
was I was at I was at the fiber shop
last night at the Revelation bible study
with brother Danny and sister Jackie
look
man they're going so deep in the word
and they're doing such a beautiful job
you got to come by and get some of this
spiritual fiber in your diet it's a
beautiful thing and just to hear
everybody interacting and brother Jack
brother Danny and sister Jackie
facilitates so well and they use
references and videos from Pastor to
kind of set up and set a good foundation
I mean they're on track beautifully
beautifully presented and uh I really
enjoyed myself there last night with
them
amen well I couldn't go uh on Sabbath
school without representing the t-shirt
message that a tante does every week so
what does my t-shirt
say faith makes all things possible well
amen Faith makes all things you know
that's a topic I like that that's a
topic we've been hearing a whole lot
about faith uh lately more and more and
more and if you're familiar with the
journey with the dream that uh sister
White had at Battle Creek and she was
talking about the journey to the to the
promised land and to the glory land for
us the more we travel you know uh with
the way things are we've heard about it
in Prophecy we know about it from
prophecy we're familiar with the
foundations of the world are being
shaken and everything is that can be
removed is being shaken right now and so
as we look around and we see so many
things seeming to be falling apart in
our world we're going to really need to
exercise this thing that God has given
us called Faith he says that the just
shall live by faith repeatedly and so
more and more this message of faith is
going to become um uh uh you know our
theme and our song Lord help us to live
by faith and keep our eyes on you
sometimes faith is all we have that's it
faith can move mountains absolutely and
as a matter of fact that's what the the
vision was about that all they had left
to hold on to were the chords that hung
down and the chords represented their
faith so so praise God and and and
speaking of faith and moving forward um
I shared with the with the prayer team
this morning in the Huddle about about
one of the passages that I love so much
Philippians chapter 3 and particularly
verse 12 where the Apostle says not that
I've apprehended but one thing I do
forgetting those things which are behind
looking forward to those things which
are before and I press forward toward
the mark for the prize of the High
Calling of God in Christ Jesus it is not
always easy to forget those things you
know I like to say you know I don't mind
looking back on my past but I refuse to
be held back by it but to get to that
place I had to
get with Jesus and learn how to have
healthy confrontation and confront the
things from my past that were once
holding me back and just to get deeper
into that today our Sabbath school is
really going to plunge into that we're
going to be looking at trauma with uh
Sister Christina Cooper who does such a
beautiful job with it she'll be with
Pastor nante want to ask you to buckle
up uh those of you who who are who are
looking forward to the new year and want
to face the new year with Victory and
confidence and and hope and just want to
make sure you've left no stone unturned
leave nothing for the enemy to to trip
you up and to sabotage your blessed life
in Christ Jesus stay tuned for this
beautiful Sabbath School amen enjoy
it we're gonna open up with prayer and
then we're going to Jump Right In yeah
so let's pray Heavenly Father uh we come
before you today Lord just thanking you
for for uh your love for us Lord we
thank you for your healing power and
Lord as we discuss this issue of trauma
um I pray Lord that you would um bring
healing to people even as they watch
even as they listen Lord um there are
many people struggling with many
different issues from the past I pray
Lord that and sometimes these issues get
in the way of our walk with Christ and
so Lord please um again just Minister
Lord through this program this morning
is our prayer in Jesus name amen
amen you know I just want to open up
again with um so many times I think well
I've seen in my you know interactions
with people doing therapy is like a lot
of times people live their life not
thinking that they experience trauma but
they've just been living life and it's
just the normal part of life and so they
just deal with it they don't really deal
with it and just think that you know
this is just normal and so the trauma
never gets dealt with
um what is your experience you know with
that in dealing with with
clients I think you're absolutely right
Tony I mean people assume that how their
lives have turned out or what they've
experienced in life it's just their
cross to bear and that they have to
continue to live with this pain for the
rest of their lives they're are people
walking around with a profound sense of
hopelessness about their circumstances
about what has happened to them in their
childhood and how those things are
impacting their current lives but they
don't know what to do about it
they um struggle in their relationships
not just with other people but their own
relationship with themselves and their
relationship with God um because of
these early experiences that created
this sense of uh lack of trust in
humanity
um because of their because of what has
happened to them and because the people
that they trusted and who were called to
protect them victimize them um and that
that's part of what we see when we're
looking at a lack of faith in people's
lives as children they learned that
people were not to be trusted and before
they even got to know that there is a
God there is a savior there is um A
Healer that is there to protect and and
restore them they don't know what to do
with that because they don't know what
that feels like they don't know what
that looks like to trust someone who is
trustworthy and so they walk around with
that pain not real not knowing what to
do with it and how experience
restoration and healing yes you know I
did um a big mistake just now I didn't
introduce you properly was so excited
and saying hey that we're friends I
didn't give your official professional
credentials so let me tell youa is and
for for those who heard her call me Tony
that was my nickname like
so no no and so no and I love it because
it tells me where our friendship goes
all the way back to so I hear like if we
went to high school together or pre high
school it's Tony if it's the like
freshman sophomore year college it's
Tony and then I became a tante with
which is my real name
okay so everyone meet Tony by the way
yeah meet Tony okay so okay but let me
tell you a little bit about Christina so
Christina um is the founder and CEO of
Sanford Global a women's leadership
development firm headquartered in
Phoenix Arizona um as an acclaimed
keynote speaker trainer and
independently licensed psychotherapist
Christina um leverages over two decades
of experience and Behavioral Sciences
and nonprofit leadership to deliver
highly energized interactive Keynotes
keynote master class and lecture series
and training programs on trauma informed
care transformational leadership
organizational Health personal
development mental health and wellness
and
spirituality so that is this is what uh
Christina does and this is why we have
her here uh today because she has you
know really put the time
into um educ herself and be um that type
of therapist for um people who are in
need of the tra trauma counseling and
again really for all of us uh we could
all learn and Clean from this because
we've all experienced some levels of
trauma on on some level um in our life
so yes um let's like you were saying
that you find that people just think
that trauma that they experienced um
they may not label it as trauma they may
just say this was just life I'm living
life and so they learned certain
behaviors throughout their life or from
childhood on just how to um just carry
on with life and not really address it
or deal with it but the trauma is
actually manifesting itself in different
areas in their life and it's causing
problems and relationships and in their
life but they they just don't know where
it's coming from or they don't care
connect it necessarily to the trauma and
when you're not aware connect it you
can't really heal or deal with it
because the point of today's program is
to help educate people like to you know
just to direct them in a way that they
will want to become aware or begin to
deal with it in the proper forms um and
to be able to deal with it and then to
ultimately become whole yes to become
whole again it's more than just healing
of the trauma it is being it is being
restored to God's original purpose for
us when he knitted before he knitted us
together in our mother's womb and so
there is a there is a complete
restoration that has to take place and
that can place when we trust God to
unveil to us the reality of our pain to
to uh make us very much aware of all of
the um nuances of how the trauma
happened and how it impacted us and what
it did to us it's so important that we
understand those things and those things
can't be done all of those things can't
be done just through therapy it requires
the Holy Spirit to reveal to you the the
depth of your um of your
Brokenness so that you can hand to him
you can surrender it to him and he can
return healing and honor and peace to
you um and so that requires a surrender
that many people who are in pain
struggle to to give up because they lost
so much control in their lives and in
their trauma that giving up control
means giving up themselves means
surrendering themselves and and put
themselves out there for additional pain
and that's a very difficult thing for
people to do but God want us to to do
that so that he can give us in exchange
for our
pain complete restoration yes yes amen I
think the song is Beauty for Ashes like
he'll take our ashes and give us um yes
that beautiful experience of true
healing well take us through the word
take us through the word and like what
does the Bible say about you know
healing trauma and even examples of that
in the absolutely um I want to start
with with uh the story of the man at the
pool of
Bethesda and if we can go there uh to
John chapter five okay vers Christa
could you just hold on one second um
sure so are you guys hearing an echo
when when uh Christina speaks yes I'm
hearing it
too if it is it's very famed I don't I
it's very F yeah I mean if uh if you all
can it's a slight Echo but it's slight
okay I can hear yeah I do hear
it it's very slight though like people
are saying it's very slight so I think
it's it's
doable okay great I'm trying to yes so
uh the man at the pool of Bethesda in
John chapter 5 we uh are introduced to
this man at the pool of Bethesda and if
we can just share or read this scripture
and this story briefly and and I will
share a little bit about
um the insights that God has given me
about this man at the pool of Bethesda
uh John chapter 5 we're starting at John
chapter 5 verses
2-9 and it says I think this is the new
King James version that I'm taking this
from so now there is at Jerusalem by the
Sheep Market a pool which is called in
the Hebrew tongue bethe
having five porches in these lay a great
multitude of impotent folk of blind halt
withered waiting for the wa for the
moving of the water for an angel went
down at a certain season into the pool
and troubled the water whosoever then
first after the troubling of the water
stepped in was made whole of whatever
disease he had and a certain man was
there which had an infirm 38 years when
Jesus saw him lie and knew that he had
been now a long time in that case he
saith unto him wilt thou be made
whole the impotent man answered him sir
I have no man when the water is troubled
to put me into the pool but while I am
coming another step is down before me
Jesus saith unto him
rise take up thy bed and walk and
immediately Ely the man was made whole
and took up his bed and walked and on
the same day was the
Sabbath and so we're seeing here the
story of a man who had been lame and
probably had other ailments that took
him
down onto the mat that he had been lying
on for 38
years he had been lying on a mat for 30
years when we look at trauma We Now
understand through studies through
science that trauma first registers in
the body yes and so when we look at this
man and we hear his story all we know is
that he's been lying on that map for 38
years but we don't know what took him
down we do know though because of what
we're learning now with increased
knowledge that trauma registers first in
the body and it impacts the body and
until it is addressed it will continue
to cause the body to
deteriorate in many different
ways so while we don't know what
happened to this man we know that
something took him down right and so
when we look at this this his condition
um trauma leaves us debilitated
it it in some ways causes us to feel as
though our lifeblood has been stolen
from
us it takes us sometimes into a place of
hopelessness and helplessness because we
don't know we know what happened but we
don't know how to cope right so we're
gonna we're gonna talk about the coping
piece a little bit later on in today's
um lesson but trauma us debilitated
similar to the man at the pool of
Bethesda except for us in today's world
we especially in America we get back up
and we keep going right right we we deal
with the trauma in a way that it com it
gets
compartmentalized meaning we're putting
it away we're putting it on the Shelf
we're putting it in a container and
setting it aside so that we can try to
move forward but there are so many
people today who are walking through
life with this deep and profound sense
of
debilitation and we call I'm sorry and
we call that strength when we like put
it in a we put it in a you know we put
it somewhere else and we don't deal with
it we just keep going yes and that's in
this Society it's considered oh you're
so strong it you know you're you're
strong you have strength yeah because
you're
not yeah and and it's not really
strength
it's I feel feel as though it's
a denial it's a self- betrayal
yeah and it is like you're saying pastor
ior um so I'm gonna throw this out here
and and see what you all think but
um is
there is there
a people come into the
church and they bring that mat with them
you understand what I'm saying and it's
it's easy to be to to say well before I
came to Christ I was you know I used to
drink or I used to smoke these physical
things that we you know muster up the
strength through the grace of God to put
away so we come into the church hey I
don't drink anymore I don't smoke
anymore but those things are very
different can see things people can see
but we have people walking around in the
church with
trauma yes and you you see the result of
it is these issues we have in the church
the the you know things that should be
happening in church that that should not
be happening in church happening in
church people getting angry over colors
of carpet and you know over things
you're like where is this coming from
and there's a sense of well when I
became a Christian
all of that is just gone yes a lot of
you know a lot of
people come you know have that mentality
that when you become a Christian that
that's just not an issue anymore um but
as a pastor dealing with people in the
congregation and dealing with people on
a personal level and seeing wow like you
know you study your Bible you do this
and that but you're still exhibiting
these types of
behavior that says something deeper is
going on so I don't know if you know we
can uh speak that or address that
because again you know and when you get
to the church it's like no you know all
you need to do is um trust God and just
keep praying yes but but that that type
of thinking goes along with the fake
strength you know what I'm saying and
I'm not when I when I say fake strength
it's not that God is not all powerful
and cannot you know heal all things but
if you don't if you're not aware don't
address it or put it away and like on
the Shelf then it's it's not open enough
for God to even begin to address it with
you yes yes um trauma is like a
vapor and if you put vapor in a
box it still comes through the crevices
right you can still see it coming
through the crevices and so it's the
same thing that happens in the church um
we have been conditioned I think in the
church to believe that when we give our
hearts to Jesus that somehow there's
this miraculous exchange that happens
between our pain and our
salvation and that really isn't true and
it's not biblical and when we come into
the church when we invite Jesus not just
coming into into the church the deeper
thing is when we invite Jesus into our
hearts right and we um make him the Lord
Of Our
Lives we are guaranteed our
salvation but our pain is to be worked
out so that's this that's that process
in uh salvational terms
is uh justification
and then sanctification justification
happens instantly you know I've been
forgiven of all the things of my past
but sanctification is the work of a
lifetime meaning there are things that
we have to work
through right on a daily
basis which is going to
include those
traumas right yes that that we
experienced as you know children or
before we came to the Lord or what have
you those things cannot be ignored they
have to be addressed and I was just
thinking something you know I
think every time you look in the Bible
and you see Jesus healing
someone they
are the issue is very
clear sick of the poliy a withered hand
they they know the
issue they know the issue and then the
question is asked Jesus can you heal me
of this
issue so is there is there some kind of
um I don't want to use the word danger
but
maybe we need to understand that we need
to know the issue so that we can ask
Jesus to heal that issue and if we
ignore or deny the issue we're never
asking
Jesus this is my sick of the paly you
know this is my this is where I'm
withered this is where I am you get what
I'm saying yeah I totally understand
what you're saying and the reason why
we're not doing that is because of how
we've been conditioned in the church to
change our
behavior and not to trans to allow God
to transform our hearts and our our
heart is the reason why our heart is
hardened is because we've been
hurt there is no other reason we have a
wounded Spirit our heart heart has been
hardened love is it's difficult for love
to flow through and it's difficult for
us to receive love because of the
hardening of our hearts which is based
in our pain and so when you talk about
um being able to identify what the pain
is and that process of sanctification
the one thing that's been missing in our
journey in this is just from my
perspective in our
journey our Christian Journey um our
spiritual journey are what we've learned
in the church is that we have um really
aligned that process of sanctification
with behavioral and performative change
and that God is not that
shallow God is much deeper than that and
he wants us to drill down into the
reasons why our Behavior our our actions
our thoughts do not align with his will
right and so though that is the the
deeper peace when it comes to
sanctification and I'm speaking from my
own perspective and my own journey in
the church I've been in the seventh day
Aven Church my entire life
sanctification has always been about
Behavior do you exhibit the fruit of the
spirit do you do this this this are you
kind gentle what and so it's all of
these things that we're trying to ensure
that we
display but we haven't
been acculturating in such a way to
understand that it's the opening of our
hearts to God that will then bring in
the light of his love clear out the the
um callous
calcified substance in our hearts and
open it back up to his love so that we
can flow and flow and
flow and so that's what I see we we have
to be able to um change the Paradigm
Shift the paradigm around our spiritual
walk so that we are understanding that
God he wants to do a complete and
thorough work in us and it starts with
our hearts not just our
Behavior so just to because what you
just said right there we can't even rush
over that that is so
fundamentally it's more than this
program what you just say um but it's
just so fundamentally like the issue
that um that we have I'll me I'll just
you know talk about like with in our
church because this is what I'm most
familiar with but and really in all
churches really but um just because the
focus is on the outside
Behavior as as as avenus right and then
not really dealing like God really wants
to deal with the um our inner heart like
where the roots of where all of that is
coming from instead of just but we just
focus so much on outer behavior and
think we're doing just fine
or this is how we deal with and we're
not really dealing with anything we're
not dealing with anything at all and
then the the undal with trauma just
comes out it just lashes out whenever it
needs to and we're like wow are we are
we Christians or are we like what are we
like you know what I mean because we're
not behaving that way at that moment in
time yeah I think uh that the the the
analogy you gave of uh the hard
heart um that doesn't allow love or has
difficulty allowing love to flow in or
flow out yes is really powerful because
you think about it when when people get
hurt you only get hurt
because you know not only but you get
hurt because of
rejection you get hurt because you
know when you get hurt your heart is
being damaged yes so think about that
hurt is not like if I get hurt
physically ow my arm hurts when you get
hurt
emotionally trauma the the the the the
body part if you will that is hurt is
the heart that's and when the heart gets
hurt it's debilitated yeah and if the
heart is meant to love now man my heart
has been hurt so much that it's hard for
me to love to let love flow out that's
right and it's hard for me to let love
flow in because I don't trust you yes
so I think what's what's powerful about
that is that that is the very essence is
you know I'm about to get like theolog
start preaching Pastor aren't you yeah
yeah I knew you would I knew you would
start preaching and there's gonna be
there's gonna be a followup sermon later
so but not today not today but in the
future in the near future I can feel it
yeah I I
think this is some history here in in
1888 our church was given a message
called called the righteousness by Faith
Message which was designed to deal with
this very issue you know righteousness
in outer
actions
versus a
transformation that is on a much deeper
level level the Heart level and uh it it
that message the righteousness by Faith
Message deals with the process of
justification and sanctification and how
the Lord Lord wants to take us deeper
and deeper and deeper he wants to reveal
the reason he's taking us deeper and
deeper and deeper is to reveal to
us um the things that we
have deep down within us yes and um I'm
remembering in particular one uh at
Jones who was one of those uh um
Messengers at Jones EJ Wagner I remember
at Jones writing and you know it's he's
writing about how the L how like sin is
like the heart is like a well and the
Lord takes us deep into that well and
the deeper we go the more frustrating
the more discouraging it can be because
we're like whoa that's there and like
yeah I need to show you more you know
think of Ezekiel you know as God is
showing him the stuff happening in the
temple in
Vision God wants to give us our own
Ezekiel
experience but we are that Temple he's
he's not trying to take us into somebody
else's Temple he's like look we're
supposed to be like wait what and he's
like wait there is yet more to show to
show you and he's taking you deeper and
deeper into your own Temple to show you
the things that are injuring our walk
with God injuring our our our ability to
love others and to be load yes yes I
want to because I know you have some
slides you want to show too and I want
to get you I because I mean the I don't
want to take you completely off track um
because I know there's some important
things that you want to share that goes
along with what we've already been
discussing but what um what does trauma
or no I want to go back trauma affects
uh the soul how does trauma affect the
soul mind and will and
emotion
so TR is a is a direct attack on Attack
on the soul and the soul is our mind our
will and our emotions and so when we're
looking at how trauma affects it when
we're looking at
um first of all our will we'll speak I
want to speak to it from the perspective
of of abuse we'll start with abuse
because there are other types of trauma
but abuse is one of the most uh common
types of trauma that we can experence
exp
erience if we've experienced abuse in
any form emotional mental
spiritual
uh physical sexual whatever those things
are the power of our will is
subverted because someone is doing
something to us that we don't want to
happen and we can't stop it right and so
that attack that direct attack on the
will affects us in that if we've
experienced abuse in any of those forms
over time and even if it just happened
once or
twice uh there becomes a question in our
mind as
to and it's not conscious it's
subconscious but am I able to carry out
my free will because we all are given a
free will
right but when it's subverted by a
perpetrator or someone who is victim is
victimizing us it comes into question
for us whether or not we have the power
to act upon our free
will when that happens when we when we
have that experience in childhood or
earlier in life when we become adults or
older adolescence we struggle to make
decisions
we struggle to tell people no when we
want to say no we say yes instead wow
because the power of our will has been
compromised by that
abuse um we struggle to
um meet the needs of others and we
betray ourselves in an effort to appease
others the reason why this is such a a
problem apart from the fact that it
creates an internal an ongoing internal
conflict inside of us is
that with that Dynamic
happening we then Veer off of the path
of our
[Music]
destiny God created
us
whole it doesn't mean that we're not
born in sin or shaped in iniquity that's
not what I'm addressing when I say whole
I mean things are
intact right okay in every way when
we're when we're born as much intact as
it can be in a sinful world and
so as children we know what we want oh
there's an ice cream cone I want that M
we're clear about what we want we say
what we want we do what we want until
we're corrected you know obviously right
but um
that Free Will is exercised in childhood
over the years and we are Guided by our
parents to uh you know operate under
some sort of
order um but the
will the will is compromised and when
our will our Free Will is
compromised it impacts our ability to
obey
God right yeah we C because inside of us
there's this internal conflict I want
this but I'm actually I've actually
through my abuse been conditioned to
meet their needs yes if you were
sexually abused or physically abused or
emotionally abused by adults in your
life see your whole Focus
becomes what can I do to ensure that the
people outside of
myself or not their will not my will
their will not my will and the reason
why that becomes an issue is because we
then become focused on our lateral
relationships and oh Jesus thank you God
we become focused on our lateral
relationships and we do so at the
expense of our relationship with God and
our Allegiance is then shifted to humans
instead of to God that's how come off of
the path of our
destiny yeah so yeah yeah can I yeah
that is powerful I mean so I'm gonna I'm
gonna I'm gonna give a practical example
of that and I'm gonna use myself and I'm
gonna be open
okay
okay because I'm listen to you may as
well yeah because this is I think this
um it
illustrates how God can heal and how
sometimes the way that in which the way
in which he heals is dealing directly
with your issue and teaching you to
trust rather in the uh uh the
relationship with him yes versus the
relationship with others so when and I
tell this in my testimony all the time
that when I was uh younger when I left
Jama
and and uh came to
America that I was bullied in a lot of
different ways because of my the way
that I spoke my heavy Jamaican accent uh
people would just made fun of me and
particularly like in the open like in
the classroom um so I was always afraid
of rejection
from masses yeah
and you know I grew up with that so I
grew up to the point of this intense
fear of speaking in public at
all
and always wanting to be you know what
is the easiest path to be approved by
other people because I was always
rejected in the classroom you know I
mean from teachers to I remember one
teacher told me I you know I had the
face only a only a mother could love
didn't know what that meant my God this
was a you know it was yeah this was kind
of like a racial thing that happened to
me at that age I had no I remember him
looking at my face smiling and just
saying it so nicely and I look back up
smiling I was like I wonder what he's
talking about yeah and things of this
nature feeling that rejection so when I
become a a a Christian an
Adventist
and the messages that that the Lord is
giving me and now I'm people are not you
know like oh look at what he's saying
you know and there's a rejection of that
message and in that rejection there's
something to me that's like no no no no
no no no like I need to make these
people happy I need to you know I need
to make sure that they understand what
I'm what I'm saying and they're probably
angry because they don't understand what
I'm
saying but in and in spite of that the
Lord is like speak what I tell you to
speak yes do what I tell you to do and
so
that has been strengthening me you see
what I'm saying throughout my Ministry
early in my Ministry down to this very
day I it's like the Lord saying I don't
care what they are saying and that is
very hard for me because I want to be
understood I want no no no what you're
thinking be accepted I want to be
accepted I want to be understood you
know I I don't want anyone ever ever
ever to be mad at me to be angry that is
like taking a
knife so just imagine that right someone
upset with me is like you may as well
take a knife and just just start doing
this to me that's how much it hurts so
when that happens on
a it's almost like the Lord's saying
here's your issue this this is how I'm
going to so this how I'm gonna fix that
issue for you because if you're so
interested in making sure people are are
happy you are never going to be healed
yourself so he gives me these messages I
speak it we hate you Pastor Mars you and
I'm just like the majority but but since
since this is his own personal
counseling
session that's what it's turned into but
but I would say that you know God the
majority of people love him of course
there's few people out there who say
that and so but because because that's
his insecurities and his where his pain
and his trauma starts from right one
person two people three people saying
that versus like thousands of saying oh
I love you those three
voices you know louder and that pain is
still there but um but from what I'm
hearing you say is that God is um is
teaching and healing your trauma through
these experiences and helping you to
become aware of because I don't think he
ever knew where that was coming from but
now he is being able to link it back to
those childhood experiences and then God
also gave him a wife that always
encourages him yes opposite and I could
I could care less about what people say
or think but so
yeah very good
example yeah it's I it's just what I've
seen over like God I believe he called
me into the ministry
partially to address that issue in me
you know so it's something I've been
going through for years and you know
like I'm used to it now like I mean even
still it it hurts but I'm just like well
whether I'm hurt or not or whether you
know being misunderstood or not God is
healing you yeah God I believe God has
has healed me that s and that's why I
was saying I would say healing that's
yeah and that's why I'm saying that this
is this is a process it's sanctification
right yes it's it's it doesn't happen in
an instant so what I'm saying is look if
if you're hearing whoa Pastor Myers you
know has issues that he struggles with
then you can know okay I'm not strange
I'm not like there's not something wrong
with me because I'm struggling too
that's right and I have say one thing
and I'm gonna let Christina go with it
that people were like oh we love your
Jamaican accent like this is not the
Jamaican accent he was teased from this
is barely nothing I mean our kids say
like he has no accent at all yeah I
barely hear it you barely barely hear it
but when he came to the this country he
his Patwa was really really bad like
even Jamaicans had a hard time
understanding him so yeah so that's what
he was teased for just clarification but
go ahead Chris yes go Ahad
um yeah I want to get back to the the
the man at the pool of Bethesda right um
the fact that he was 38 years in bondage
um his hopelessness I have no man that
what that's what he said I have no man
when the water is troubled to put me
into the pool he was dependent on people
he didn't recognize that his healing
actually would come from God and so he
wasn't looking to God for his answer he
was looking to um some spiritual I don't
know whether it was Superstition or
whether it was true we won't know until
we see Jesus and ask hey that man at the
pool of Bethesda was there an angel who
would come and heal like we don't know
whether it was Superstition or whether
it was a real phenomenon that was H was
happening spiritually at that time
but
um regardless of what it was he was
trusting things outside of of himself
outside of what God had placed inside of
him right if he was a Believer at that
time he also he was very much trusting
in man which a lot of us do when we're
trying to to move through our
trauma right here's the thing there's a
balance and I want people to know this
because I hear so many Christians say
you don't need God to do you don't need
man to do anything you don't need a
therapist I mean God is gonna heal you
just go directly to him and then he will
heal you um and then there are people
who say you need to see a therapist
otherwise you will not be healed right
so there are these two sort of um
dichotomous ideal about where your
healing is going to come from God uses
people to speak through people through
his holy spirit to help you to heal but
that the actual process of healing is a
miracle it is a miracle that comes
directly from God the therapist can
invite you in to a safe environment
where your brain can heal from trauma
which we'll talk about at some other
time but your brain is injured when you
are experence when you've experienced
trauma and your brain is healed in the
context of a safe supportive consistent
relationship your literal brain parts of
your brain get healed and restored
through the relationship with your
therapist or someone else who is also
very safe and supportive and consistent
so there is healing that takes place in
our bodies as a result of trusting other
people to help us to heal but your
wholeness is a miracle that will come
directly from
God uh I I'm thinking in terms of the
Commandment the two great Commandments
uh love God with all your all your heart
love your neighbor as yourself and it it
it I think what you're saying is that
healing must come on those two levels
yes one
which uh requires healing between you
and God what whatever your
misconceptions of him are whatever your
fears of him are and then the other is
your relationship with Humanity that's
right must include other people it
must you can't on that
level isolated that's right so um yeah
and I don't know if you you're seeing
the the the comments or the questions
there's been a lot of questions coming
up in the the chat and
okay you're not seeing the questions at
all so we'll put some up there as yeah I
think so comments yes I really want her
to highlight because we're um there's
seven steps to Healing yes there are yes
so we want to look at that we want
people to to lead here with like
encouragement and hope and so we want to
begin to look at that um I don't know if
if do you have a slide for that SL yes I
do have slides for that
all right so can we um I think um our
producer Patrice has those slides can we
can put one of those up okay here it
goes there we go thank
you so I'm gonna skip over some of these
learning objectives because we have
learned a lot already in our
conversation okay let's just let's just
start just fundamentally just for
background okay what is trauma because
we hear it all the time a lot of people
believe that trauma is is excuse me is
an event that occurs that is you know oh
I got in a car accident oh I was
physically abused I was sexually abused
I was emotionally abused those are
actions that happen but trauma is the
emotional response that we have to those
things those very distressing things for
which we lack the ability to
cope it becomes trauma when we when the
trauma supersedes our ability to cope
it's not just what happens it's whether
or not we can cope determines whether or
not we have experienced trauma so trauma
is an emotional
response to a deeply distressing event
or series of events that exceeds our
ability to cope that's why when you hear
some people say like oh I grew up
totally impoverished we had to eat you
know beans all day long and we were on
food stamps and we had this and we lived
in you know a really bad neighborhood
and all of that and they're like but I
mean I'm fine and they really are fine
because it didn't exceed their ability
to cope right they didn't experience
trauma as a result of the of what was
happening and so that is when we know
that trauma is is um present is when it
exceeds the person's ability to
cope we talked about earlier that trauma
registers in the body first and when we
look at this man at the pool of
Bethesda
um there there there was a lot there
that we could uncover about his
experience but the fact that he was
physically debilitated which we talked
about I want to reference this quote
from Bessel Vander he's a leader in
trauma recovery in trauma understanding
trauma in general
and he he wrote the book the body keeps
the score which I see someone referenced
in the comments yeah HZ people
chronically feel unsafe in their
bodies the past is alive in the form of
gnawing interior
discomfort their bodies are constantly
bombarded by visceral warning signs and
in an attempt to control these processes
they often become expert at ignoring
their gut feelings
remember we talked about that internal
conflict that happens when you've been
abused you fight between honoring
another person's desires and their will
and honoring your own so you typically
end up betraying your own in order to
appease others um Bessel Vander Coke
says that they often become expert at
ignoring their gut feelings and in
numbing awareness of what is played out
inside they learn to hide from their
selves and so that's one of the critical
um manifestations of how trauma shows up
in the body and how we respond to it
relationally we feel it in our bodies
and because of what we've gone through
we have learned to ignore it right we've
learned to disregard it we've learned to
um pretend it's not there and in doing
so we become even more abilitate our
relationships break down even more
because when we're in these
relationships we don't we're not really
telling the people that we're in
relationship with the truth about how we
feel what we desire what we
need we don't know how to do that
because trauma creates walls around our
heart to protect us once it happens and
so it's very difficult like you said we
don't let our when we're in a
relationship we don't let the person
that we are in love with or or you know
the family whatever that we have a close
relationship with we only let them in so
close and then they might jump one
barrier one wall but they canot jump all
the walls if the trauma has not been
dealt with so you can never really get
as close into the into the person's
heart that we don't allow them to get
into our heart as closely because we're
just that wall is there to protect yes
absolutely can can we look at that
question right there just real quick I
see that yes
yeah she Kim Kimberly says can we it
just went away there it is Kimberly Cruz
says can this be why some people sleep
so much is that the one you were
referring to Pastor okay because their
body is exhausted from feeling
unsafe it's definitely possible Kimberly
because when you're operating in a state
of heightened arousal is what we arousal
meaning you're on
alert um it's exhausting to your nervous
system your whole nervous system your
limic system is
all sort of hijacked by yeah gone
through and so that feeling of just
being like I just want to sleep I just
feel exhausted I'm emotionally exhausted
can I just sleep for like three days
straight that's what I just want that's
what I desire part it could be because
there is unresolved trauma that needs to
be processed and sleep is a way to not
just avoid it
um but to re to somehow rest to somehow
rest and that takes me back to this um
this this story about the man at the
pool of
Bethesda the mat when we're looking at
the mat and we're looking
at
um when when Jesus said take up thy
bed right take up thy bed the bed
represents a place of rest a place of
Peace a place of renewal
Rejuvenation restoration these are all
things that happen in the bed or on our
bed or on in this case his mat and so
Jesus was saying to him in that moment
you no longer have to be bound
debilitated or um floored and completely
flattened by what has occurred in your
life you can now take up your
bed and
you can take it up you no longer need
this I am now giving you the rest that
you desperately need the rest that I
promised right right yeah giving you
that rest and you can now move forward
in your life putting one foot in front
of the other walking in your healing
your wholeness and your
restoration yeah wow that's good it's
beautiful and so trauma looks like
our neglect
assault chronic illness it is traumatic
people don't think this but or recognize
this I don't think but when you're when
you're experiencing a chronic illness it
is traumatic the diagnosis is trauma
hearing the diagnosis is traumatic
trying to figure out what you're going
to do about it is traumatic hearing your
prognosis is traumatic trying to put
everything together so that you can
create a life for yourself that promotes
healing that's
challenging yes I know Tony you know
this because of your own experience
but it to speak to that a little bit
about how that can be
traumatic yes um you're you're speaking
of of my multiple sclerosis diagnosis
that you're okay I'm sorry no no no it's
okay it's okay it's okay I was like been
traumatizing other but no no yes no no
no but then no no it is it was um being
diagnosed but you know what I mean I
feel like this is our own counseling
session but no no but yes originally
originally when it first happened I
didn't even know what multiple sclerosis
was so even hearing the doctor
say um you know it possibly could be
this I was like what is that and then I
start going through my mind and doing
some research and it just scares you you
know have I had no idea um so yes it was
very
traumatizing um at first and and and to
be honest to be honest it's still tra
because it's still traumatizing when
people when I go to the doctor and they
say oh your blood work is great right
when I first went to the doctor they
said oh your I'll never forget the
doctor the ER doctor said oh your blood
work is Stellar that's what he said and
then the other doctor said but just in
case we want to send you to a
neurologist just in case you know and
then I get like a couple days later like
this big new I was like wait I thought
my blood work was Stellar what happened
so but so even when um we still to this
day like might have to go to the doctor
and they say oh you're doing fine in the
back of my mind I'm like okay am I
really doing fine you know the that that
little it's still there but yes it was
definitely traumatizing in the very
beginning um and God had to like take me
on that that journey and absolutely
absolutely so things that we may not not
we may not attach to trauma are actually
attached to trauma because again it's
not what's happening it's whether or not
what is happening exceeds our that our
current ability to cope with it and so
so chronic illness is on that list
miscarriage let let me let me ask real
quick so then trauma is not necessarily
something that is uh limited to your
early years right your formative years
it can be
div know events that happen yeah it can
be all of those things it can be
miscarriage it can be abortion it can
there's something called post traumat
postabortion
trauma you know I have a friend that um
from high school who had multiple
abortions in high school and our
freshman year I think we were in college
she started having horrible nightmares
about her baby sitting at the of the
stairs with blocks looking up the stairs
at her and say saying mommy why did you
kill me recurring dreams these this is
what trauma looks like this is what that
post-abortion trauma looks like you're
you're trying your brain and your body
are trying to recover from what has
happened and it happen it people have
effects of it even males have effects
from postabortion trauma if it was their
child that was aborted so there are so
many things with that abandonment that's
what tra trauma looks like that it looks
like chronically unmet needs in our
childhood in our relationships it looks
like breakups it looks like
divorce it looks like a hostile work
environment these are all things that
look this is when these things happen
trauma is our response to these
[Music]
things and then what does do it feel
like what does it feel like it feels
like replaying memories in our minds
having nightmares just this overarching
overwhelming sense of fear and anxiety
always feeling on edge never able to
relax um not being able to
laugh you know those things you're
you're uncomfortable with people
cracking jokes or you know being funny
you're like oh you're you're in this
state where you just want to be um in
control
and laughter laughter is an alternative
um it's an alternate
State we change from our current state
into a state of laughter that's changing
states so when people are laughing it
feels uncomfortable because you're like
I can't control they're changing states
this is
not right flashbacks anger and when I
say anger it's not the emotion of anger
that lets us know that we're
experiencing trauma but many times it's
rage
rage yeah someone just asked if it could
be manifested in
depression absolutely yeah absolutely
your anger even anger is depression is
really anger turned inward in many cases
so when you're looking at um depression
yes depression can happen as a result of
unresolved trauma because you are
holding all that energy in all of that
those feelings and thoughts in without
processing them and
then your your chemical makeup your of
your body changes as a result of some of
that your outlook on life changes and
you could become depressed guilt
numbness you start to avoid people
places and things related to the trauma
you start to believe the world is an
extremely dangerous place right and you
have difficulty trusting
people yes what is that last the the
last point there they were saying it was
blocked they couldn't see it the last
one difficulty trusting people okay
that's the last okay yeah okay excuse me
I you're running out of time so that's
why I
want right yeah I mean we yeah I'm just
gonna we can keep we have we have some
time keep going because I want you to
get to the seven yes the seven
yes I do and this is just something for
for us to think about you know I see
there's some people asking you know if
this channel offers help if it offers
counseling and it's something that we so
we need to yeah I didn't see those
questions so you know we're I mean
Christine and I are both mental health
professionals but we're not your mental
health professionals and so if you are
after listening to uh this information
and presentation you're feeling like
you're needing some mental health um you
know care care individual care then
definitely we encourage you to seek out
mental health Counseling in your local
area um because that's if you're feeling
that you need that um that's very
important for you to take the next step
to to reach out to a mental health uh
professional that can assist you but yes
this is education this is for Education
basis and so that um you can get
education here of course on our mental
health Mondays we do this as well um so
yeah that's what we offer is mental
health educ
here uh but if you're feeling like you
need to speak to someone definitely
reach out to a mental health
professional in your area yes and you
can do that by going to
psychologytoday.com Yes um that's the
main Hub of all of us therapist if we're
in private practice at all you can find
someone in your area who takes your
insurance and um who deals with your
specific issue you can type in your
issue and it will come up with a
therapists in your area who address that
specific issue and I also want to say to
that too because some people say like oh
I can't afford therapy I don't have
insurance that will cover therapy so you
will also be able to find I mean there's
great County County resources that are
could be very inexpensive there's also
um on psychology today there's
therapists in training to get their
licenser and so they're you know
Associates or even interns you can and
there and so the cost of the therapy is
ex extremely um inexpensive and can be
affordable to to your income so don't
let income keep you out not to to reach
out for therapy and let me let me add
this also that I think probably a
greater underlying issue is
the uh
stigma of well if you're a
Christian why do you need
counseling um and so I think that's yeah
that's something that is kind of
it it's looked down upon um and maybe
that's beginning to change now but you
know I would say not for this generation
but our generation and the generation
prma this generation they're here for
counseling but oh yes the priors the
ones who braced yes we didn't want to go
to counseling it's it's demonic you you
just have a demonic issue you know just
about it so you know
be I'm saying
don't let shame prevent you from seeking
the help or Pride even or Pride I'm a
Christian or I'm Pastor I'm you know all
that and you know we know that there are
a lot of different counselors that are
that are you know you you want to find
someone that that is in line with your
faith and in line with what you believe
and that's fine as well I think you can
actually you know they'll tell you
whether they're Christian or not or so
just just I'm just saying don't be
ashamed to get
help if you need that help and I would
just say there's just good therapists
out there whether I mean there's good
Christian therapists that I I've worked
with amazing Christian therapist they
don't have they're not Adventists but
they're amazing Christian therapists I
worked with therapists who aren't
Christian at all but you know have all
the fundamentals that yes and they also
help you they also can help you
they yes
so yes I know so I'm like
um let's look a little bit before we go
into the seven um steps to recovering
from trauma the unresolve childhood
trauma in adults what does it feel like
it feels like
self-blame when something goes wrong we
automatically assign it to ourselves
whether it had anything to do with us or
not um we do a lot of Shing on ourselves
we should I should have done this I
should have done that shouldn't have
happened this and so the way to
experience peace in your life is to give
God your shoulds to exchange your
shoulds for what
is when we do that we come in right
relationship with God because we're
looking at the truth instead of what
should be we're actually addressing the
truth um and we're and we're getting
under getting a greater understanding or
right estimation of ourselves in of our
relationship so give your shoulds to God
and he give back to you what is and then
you can start doing the
work I wanna do this I want to say this
and I don't know what your schedule's
like Christina I don't know we didn't
talk about this and we haven't talked
about this we're gonna talk about it
right now with everybody because I don't
want you to rush I don't want you to
rush and this is so I'm seeing there's
so many great questions out there and I
know how much healing and then again
we're not your therapist but just from
this information beginning process of
healing can take Start begin to take
place and you can start to make a
decision to reach out to a mental health
professional but I don't want you to
even rush through these seven I mean we
can start it here I'm thinking we should
do a part two next week and we don't
have to end right here right here but we
can I want you to I want you to kind of
just to rush over that childhood trauma
how it impacts you as an adult I we
can't rush over that yeah
so there
um so yeah is that a yes
husband so um so yes and that's a you
yes too Christina you're you're good a
yes okay everybody this is just part one
so I interrupted you continue and then
we'll we'll close it off in like five
minutes but we'll continue next week to
continue going go ahead okay that sounds
good um oh I feel better now because I
was like oh let's hurry up um we were
causing anxiety for Christina guys we
have to like we can't cause
anxieties um so yeah we we experience
that Shing and we do a lot of self-
judgment when we've had a childhood
trauma that's unresolved we have these
profound feelings of inadequacy and
worthlessness um this isn't something
that if someone were to come up to us
and say do you feel worthless and
inadequate most people would say
no right of course they're not going to
say I feel worthless and inadequate yeah
the way that the in the feelings of
inadequacy and worthlessness show up are
in how we relate to other people and how
we treat
ourselves and so when we are feeling
inadequate we're not speaking up in our
relationships we're not saying what
isn't going to work for us um we are
allowing the people whom we love to
sort of um take control in the
relationship and we become sort of this
backseat passenger as the relationship
moves forward and none of what's
happening in the relationship are we
okay with right so that is an indicator
that there is a level of worthlessness
that is present in your psyche in your
in your belief system and when I'm
saying belief system I'm not talking
talking about your uh spiritual belief
system but about your core belief system
what you believe about yourself in the
context of your
relationships when we have worthlessness
or experience
that sometimes the core belief system or
what's written on our internal slate is
other people's opinions mean more to me
than my
own what someone else thinks about me is
more important than what I believe about
myself I or or what God thinks about us
yes yes um I don't deserve to have a
voice in this relationship because in
any number of things could be there
because I made mistakes in the past
because I you know uh did something
wrong becau whatever those things are um
those are some of the things that can be
a backdrop to to how we engage in our
relationships and how we um get our
needs met in our relationship some of us
because of our worthlessness believe
that the only way to get our needs met
in a relationship is to manipulate and
control because our needs were never met
in our childhood willingly by a
caregiver or a
parent wow and so when that happens in
our childhood when our parents do not
anticipate our needs which is their
responsibility to do when we're children
we go into
adulthood who we we learn how to either
ignore our needs and our wants we become
needless and
want or we learn to manipulate our way
into getting our needs met and neither
of those are healthy
because when we're needless and
want um it's easier to be needless and
want than to be hurt by not getting the
need that we had so why don't I just
pretend I don't have any needs then we
don't have to deal with the
pain and then some and then sometimes
that can turn into us making decisions
to get into relationships that become
abusive either emotionally or physically
because you are used to not getting your
needs met so you just allow this person
to mistreat you that's right that's
exactly right that's exactly right and
Tony there that could be an entirely
an hourong workshop on that's I know
it's a whole
thing that's a whole thing yeah we feel
constantly on guard uh that's some of
that post-traumatic stress that shows up
we may be easily startled by certain
things um we may see danger
everywhere right if I know I'm gonna do
this slide and then um yeah then we can
close because I want to tell this story
toward the end okay okay seeing danger
everywhere
um real quick just let me I want to
address something in the in the chat
real quick um so Patty if you could
email
Patrice um and let us know about your
situation uh that would be helpful okay
but she needs to see patrice's email so
that's gonna go on the screen for you so
you can see that so a lot of people are
asking how they can how they can assist
besides prayer okay so okay okay go
ahead Christina go ahead okay
um when we're looking at seeing danger
everywhere this is one of the signs and
symptoms of unresolved childhood trauma
and what it looks like in our
adulthood um there's a story that came
from The Twilight Zone from literally
years ago it's the black and white
version of The Twilight Zone it's a
story of a man and wife who live who
were recently married um they lived in a
mobile home or a manufactured home
whatever you want to call it
today and they had just been married um
the wife was so excited to like you know
be a good wife to her husband he worked
and she stayed home and um one night he
worked he had to work till late in the
evening till the next day he had to work
overtime that particular night it was
early in their
marriage
and that particular night her husband
left the mobile home left their home and
that night an intruder came in and
assaulted the
woman the next day as the sun was coming
up her husband was returning from um
work and she was lying on the bed in
their mobile home obviously traumatized
distraught sort of curled up in a few
position and he the husband is like what
happened to you what's wrong and so she
told him what happened and the husband
became very much angry and enraged and
said to her what did he look like what
did your as salent look
like tell me all about him because we're
going to drive through the town and
we're going to find
him the ass salent uh was a darkhaired
tall individual with a white shirt
on they drive through the town and the
husband is driving saying honey is that
him honey and she's like no no no and
then she finally says there he is that's
him that's him that's the one who came
in and he hurt
me he pulls the car over and goes to
attack the man he attacks the man he
hurts the man he ends up killing the
man they get back in the car and he's
like oh I'm so glad that this is over
over now no one will ever hurt you
again they turned the car around to go
back home to their home their community
and they're driving down the street and
the last scene in that show was the
woman looking to the
side onto the sidewalk to a man who was
tall with dark hair and a white shirt on
and she pointed to him and said that's
him there he
is and the lights go
[Music]
down when we've experienced trauma that
has not been resolved many times we see
danger everywhere even in people who are
not there to hurt us
mercy and that's why we have to be so
careful to acknowledge and honor our
pain and to deal with it because if we
don't there is a a widespread effect
that it can have on us and every around
us
wow I wanna end there I
wanna
wow I'm gonna end there you know they
teach us in therapy sometimes it's good
to just sit in silence with the client I
feel like this is a good time to just
sit in silence that that was such a
powerful uh story that analogy that just
proves the point so I mean it just wow I
am so thankful that we're going to I'm
thankful for what you've shared so far
I'm thankful that we can continue next
week to go deeper I know those who are
viewing um have been blessed and um are
looking forward to what's going to be
shared next week please share this
please share this on your social media
and let them know that there's going to
be a part two um and definitely come
back for the part two because we're
going to try to cover uh the seven um
seven ways to heal from trauma um but
also we may be able to take some of your
questions as well um in the part two so
Christina thank you thank you thank you
for having me today it's been an honor
yes information that you're sharing is
invaluable did you want to share com
yeah I'm just gonna uh I'm just gonna
address very quickly okay uh Kathy
Matthews she said so do you think it
could be possible that adults that study
the Bible truths and are frightened by
them cause trauma that they see danger
everywhere uh that's a whole different
subject right there Kath I just want you
to know we're gonna be addressing that
in the future yes so it's a very
significant we're we're gonna be dealing
with trauma in a religious context
spiritual trauma spiritual trauma so but
I like this trauma series that we're
doing with Christina is a great
introduction to that it's a great
introduction to that on that um yes so
thank you thank you for being willing to
come again next week we look forward to
that um be before we go before we close
in prayer I just want to remind everyone
to or invite them to continue to worship
with us as we are going to enter into
our divine uh worship um experience but
also to let you know that if you have
any prayer requests please put it in the
chat our prayer team is looking and
watching just to gather your prayer
request brother Terry will be praying
over them um in the Divine worship time
so please put your prayer requests in
the chat also for those of you who want
to join us after the sermon for the uh
Afterglow time please um if you have not
downloaded alter live but you want to
join us for the Afterglow please
download alter live which will be uh
going across your screen or in the chat
here in just a moment um and so that
time is uh just really a blessing
because there's testimonies there's
prayer you get reflection of what you've
learn learned in the S what people have
learned in the Sabbath school today and
also in the sermon so they could talk
about their whole worship experience and
what you know God has done for them
through this worship experience so
please join us um in the altar livetime
after uh the sermon and put your prayer
request if you have one in the
chat in the northeast corner of Africa
lies a country Fame for its historic
ruins incredible monuments Rich culture
giant pyramids and friendly
[Music]
people a country covered by the largest
desert on the planet the Sahara Desert
Egypt is arid sunny and Dusty a true
desert the N River the lifeblood of
Egypt is the most important means for
supporting life in this harsh climate
this father of African Rivers is the
longest river in the world covering an
astounding
4,132 Mi it truly is the Wellspring the
sustainer of life in this historic Hot
Spot most life cannot survive in the
desert landscape of Egypt and yet Egypt
is known in history for being a thriving
superpower of antiquity the seed of all
other civilizations they were the master
Engineers well advanced in their time
they built their monuments as a
testament to their genius power and
pride they wanted to be remembered
forever just south of Cairo on a rocky
Plateau on the West Bank of the N River
sits the Pyramids of Giza the only
surviving wonder of the ancient world
there are three pyramids here each one
built to house the mummified bodies and
the physical Goods of three generations
of pharaohs father son and Grandson the
walls are inscribed with pictures and
texts of almost every subject imaginable
to this day scientists aren unsure
exactly how the Egyptians built these
ancient relics they stand as a testament
to their architectural skill and genius
near the Great Pyramids stands one of
the world's largest monuments the Great
Sphinx this colossal statue was carved
out of a single piece of sandstone
although it has deteriorated over the
centuries this ancient Relic is still
very much intact and it is incredible
sight to behold the city of luxer sits
Brad upon the banks of the na River it
is here that onethird of the world's
ancient monuments are found the Valley
of the Kings the Temple of luxer the
Temple of carac the Valley of the Queens
are just a few of the iconic sites you
can visit in this open air museum temple
ruins Royal burial grounds ancient
monuments are scattered across this
desert landscape there are some of the
oldest remaining monuments in the world
what's amazing about it is that they
built it in a time when they didn't have
electricity or power tools they only had
pulley and manpower to accomplish what
they did with the technology that they
had is nothing short of amazing it gives
us a glimpse into the engineering Genius
of this ancient civilization these
structures have stood the test of time
but why was the ancient civilization so
successful and Powerful how are they
able to build these incredible monuments
instead of Simply laboring for survival
in this harsh desert land that which all
these monuments have in common is that
they were built near the water the great
now River is the lifeline of ancient
Egypt being used as a source of food
water transportation and irrigation for
crops without denial life would not have
been possible in this region of the
world without the Nile they would never
have the time or ability to erect these
massive monuments their life and their
legacy was built on the banks of the
Nile the lesson is simple but profound
in its Simplicity if you want to survive
and thrive in life like the ancient
Egyptians you need to your life with an
environment most favorable for Success
if you want the Temple of your legacy
and the Monument of your influence to
remain long after you're gone you need
to build by the river the place most
favorable for growth and prosperity it's
all about location now you may not have
had the chance to choose the literal
location of where you live but there are
many other areas in life where we do
have the power to decide like who we
surround oursel with what we put in
front of our eyes The Voice es we choose
to listen to what we consume physically
mentally and spiritually the friends and
influencers we choose to follow these
are the things that we can't control we
must stop setting up our tents in the
desert of lifeless thinking we need to
avoid mentally habituating in the
sifting sinking sand of selfish worldly
philosophy that's constantly changing
with the blowing Winds of empty trends
of vain importance a house cannot stand
when its foundation nation is sinking
sand like the ancient Egyptians if we
want our house to stand and the legacy
of our monuments to last for Time and
Eternity we must build our lives and our
Legacy near the river for it is a Life
and Legacy built by the river that will
impact future Generations we must set
Our Roots down by the river we must feed
upon the life-giving Water of positive
thinking gratitude in times of
difficulty delayed gratification
self-sacrifice
faith hope and a Heavenly love that is
demonstrated in service to others these
are the characteristics that will
Outlast the elements for the god that
came to this ancient land many
generations ago gave to all of us the
promise that when we walk not in the
Council of the ungodly when we stand not
in the path of Sinners when we avoid
sitting in the seat of the scornful but
instead Delight in his ways and meditate
upon his righteousness day and night
that as a result we shall be like a tree
planted by the rivers of water whose
leaves are always green and fruit is
always tasty and whatever we do will
prosper and so I invite you today to
come out of the desert ignore the
deceptive Mirage that will leave you
unsatisfied Come to the River of Life
now you may not be able to come to the
Nile like we've done so today but there
is another River that is within the
reach of a there is a river whose stream
shall make glad the city of God the holy
place of the Tabernacles of the most
high the unmovable Monument of your life
is built by the river of God's grace and
the water of his Divine favor all can
come all can drink you need not be a
pharaoh to have a monument named after
you all you must do is come by faith to
the King of Kings from whose Throne
flows the River of Life and there he
will give you everything that you need
to overcome the challenges and thrive in
the desert of this world so go where the
water flows it is the best place to sew
and the place most favorable to grow and
when your fruit begins to show then all
will know and they too will be drawn to
where the water
[Music]
flows we hope you've been blessed and
inspired by this new reflections of Hope
episode this episode is one of many
that's been produced all over the world
if you haven't done so yet please give
our video a like share it with your
friends and please follow us on
Instagram Facebook and YouTube if you'd
like to see more inspiring episodes and
get access to much more uplifting
content please go now to
patreon.com revelation of Hope and sign
up to be a member of our patreon page
your monthly support will not only give
you early access to many more inspiring
videos but it will also enable us to
continue to produce more of these cin
atic object lessons from nature our goal
is to produce and release these episodes
much more frequently so please
prayerfully consider partnering with us
so that we may continue to share the
hope of Jesus all over the world thank
you so much for your support Aloha and
Marin
[Music]
[Applause]
he
[Music]
welcome back living Mana church family
or welcome if you're just tuning in
thank you so much for joining our last
Divine service of
2024 it's what an incredible year right
amen what an incredible Sabbath school
and what a blessing that we can go back
and review that again if we would like
to um please put a one in the chat if
you are visiting us for the very very
first time and again if you would like
to put where you are tuning in from we
would love to know where you are one of
the amazing things about having a
virtual online Global church is we get
to uh fellowship with people all the way
around the world so that is so exciting
Jerry is here from San Diego we love you
Jerry amen always
Angela we we I think you're in St Louis
St Louis yeah amen sister Angela amen uh
uh C Madson from Oregon we didn't miss
you earlier Sister Lisa Marie from Long
Island New York we saw you brother Elco
from cure South uh uh sister Jackie
Wilson from Louisiana wenderland Vines
from Seattle uh Tacoma and uh Angela
Swanson we saw you earlier from uh
Washington Concrete Washington welcome
welcome man don't want to forget Ida
gami from vicilia California right we're
only a few hours away from you they're
in the Central sanen Valley over there
yes Michelle Barkley Madson from Happy
Valley Oregon hello Michelle Robert from
Romulus Michigan by way of luk Texas
Hallelujah welcome Robert that's two for
you today brother Robert Elder Robert
Barbara stetina from Mountain View oh
Barbara we are from San Jose not too far
from there so we love Mountain View amen
welcome and look can I just say a a
shout out to my warri yetes in the chat
sister blessings Sister Yana Sister
Christina sister Jacqueline all y'all be
in that chat and we thank God for you I
see I see brother Tom I see Tom and Joor
Fisher there love y'all love y'all and
uh sister Patrice Hallelujah yes it is a
roll call here roll call number one roll
call number two always comes during
pray well maybe not today I don't know
Joanne from Trinidad and Tobago in the
house we love you coach jojoen Denise
Richardson from beautiful South Florida
listen I was going to give you a shout
out sister Denise because last night
great input there at the Revelation
bible study with sister Jack and brother
Danny uh uh I call it the uh uh fiber
shop because that's what we don't rush
through there we go deep in the word and
get that fiber so praise God Ramona from
St Louis and Carrie Jano from Washington
State welcome welcome welcome well we're
gonna get into the announcements but
before we do yes I gotta get one more
shout out for the South Carolina crew
that's my home and I know all y'all here
I see you sister Ashley Owens I know
you're there Sister Christina usually
there so em Wright you're usually in the
chat you know hey Carolina roll call
today
oh I don't want to miss Diane Martinez
from Fort Worth Texas and thank you to
those who have been praying for all the
prayer requests in the chat we see it
and we thank you so much please share
this broadcast with your friends and
loved ones that's the amazing thing of
being on all of these social networks
we're able to share with our family and
friends amen so let's get into the
announcements the first announcement
let's stay connected
and this
is um for America only get text alerts
and announcements about what is going on
at Living Mana Church please send a text
to
8552071892 and you will never miss
anything it's just helpful to plug into
our services and programs and this will
be a easy way of getting alerted um for
Americans then there is mighty networks
so this is for announcements for
everyone including everyone in different
countries we are um really encouraging
everyone in the US and all around the
Globe to sign up for Mighty networks
because this is our virtual Church home
and this is available to everyone see
upcoming announcements get plugged into
small groups we have the women's chat
that is so interactive and Lively the
men's group who cover important topics
that men face in an encouraging and safe
environment our gems group for our more
mature adults our recovery small group
we have so much going on in Mighty
networks we have a 24-hour prayer wall
there we have just opportunities to plug
into our church Community make friends
and build relationships there's a lot of
info going on over there so plug into
mighty networks amen living Mana online
church
kids man I'll tell you this is an hour
and a half of fun for your children
every Sabbath um you can send a text to
kids to 8552741386
[Music]
such a blessing for your children so uh
definitely plug your kids in
membership if you are already a 7th Day
Adventist you can request a transfer
from your local church to living Mana
online Church by sending an email to
Patrice Patrice living mana. live if you
are already baptized and would like to
become a member you can do a profession
of faith and become a
that way or if you aren't baptized yet
you can request to do studies with
Pastor Ivor Meers in the Bible workers
and schedule your baptism and become a
member that way so there are three ways
to join living Mana online
church if you would like to have a
oneon-one meeting with pastor Ivor
Meyers there are Virtual Office hours
you can send an email to Patrice living
Mana . church and she will schedule an
appointment so you can speak with your
pastor prayer
requests this is a way that you can
submit your prayer requests your praise
reports you can join our prayer team or
a special ops prayer team under the
prayer team umbrella and our amazing
prayer warriors collect all your prayers
and pray for you throughout the week you
can also share your answered prayer so
that others can find Hope and
encouragement for their own prayers by
sending an email to pray Living mana.
Church or text pray for to 85527407474
[Music]
Mana Channel get plugged into our chat
there we are growing our Channel and
would so appreciate if you would
subscribe and like all of the recordings
of the sermons are there as well as
recordings of our weekly programming
like mental health Monday for example
you can share the sermons and
programming with your loved ones from
the living Mana YouTube channel so
follow and like at my living
Mana now
I am so excited for this oh my goodness
the convocation is coming in Orlando
Florida from May 1st through 4th you can
scan the QR code to register and book
your hotel rooms we are suggesting you
book sooner than later as I'm sure there
are a lot of people that are going to
register you can uh this QR code will go
directly to the page where you can um
register for your hotel rooms there's
registration packages available that
include events Beverages and a gift bag
purchase of meal tickets so you can
enjoy the delicious food throughout the
event we'll be having amazing speakers
like Dr Ricardo white and messages to
feed you spiritually fun events baptisms
for those who would like to be baptized
and a crystal and glass themed gala
where you have the chance to dress up
and get fancy or at least wear your best
Church attire but best of all and what
I'm looking forward to the most the
fellowship and meeting each other face
to face I cannot wait to hug you guys in
person lots of fun things planned and in
store for you so don't miss out the link
should be in the living Mana YouTube
chat and if you don't know how to scan
the QR code just open your camera on
your phone and aim it at the QR code and
click on the link that pops up on your
camera screen or you can take a photo of
this screen save your photo to your
album on your phone press and hold down
the QR code with your finger and a
window should pop up that says open in
Safari or your default web browser but
we are looking forward to seeing you in
Orlando and hopefully that helps you uh
with instructions on how to access that
QR code and then I'm going to pass the
rest of the announcements off to Terry
well amen we're also excited to announce
the launch of a new living Mana podcast
called safe place this brand new podcast
will be hosted by our the living Mana
young adult Pastor Lami Richardson and
so we want to invite you to join Pastor
Richardson as he creates a welcome and
secure environment where young adults
can openly discuss you know challenges
and and triumphs of everyday life
everything from relationships mental
health to career goals and spiritual
growth it's just going to be a safe
place and so safe place really just
covers it all you know with empathy
wisdom and a touch of humor and as you
heard this morning from uh Sister
Christina Cooper you know humor can just
be that thing that changes that state
long enough to make these serious
challenges of young people a little more
bearable and and and I love the fact
that they're using humor that's why it's
because humor can be a way to really a
vehicle for hope to get in there and
make it more bearable so we want to
really uh each of these episodes are are
going to be are going to feature like a
special guest real life stories
practical advice gonna make it it's a
you know this is really a must-watch for
anyone who's seeking guidance and
community so we want to invite you to
tune in subscribe and be a part of the
supportive journey together and so I
think our first episode is going to be
dropping on January 9th uh 2025 so stay
tuned and uh come on in and join us for
that and so you're seeing all that's
going on here at Living mana and again
we always are excited about living Mana
Global the last couple weeks we've been
watching um videos and you've been
seeing this amazing program what it's
doing and allowing us to take the the
Everlasting gospel around the globe in
seven different languages it's amazing
to see it there's a lot involved with it
and really this this this is such a
powerful tool for living Mana and we
we're thankful for it we we saw the
video of Pastor in Arabic I believe and
we saw in Spanish maybe Korea I think
it's just wonderful because it's more
than just playing a track there you know
there's uh that program really uses his
voice and it kind of follows the lips
and and then we have the translators
behind the scene who are familiar with
the languages that he's speaking in to
make sure that we are actually covering
all of the nuances and the idioms of the
language that is being spoken in so
really amazing and the slides that's
right and the slides have to be
translated thank you for reminding me of
that that's right and first ladyes
always reminding us those slides are in
those languages and so if you know
someone that speaks uh either Spanish
French Korean Arabic any of the language
that Lo living Mana Global uh is
covering share the link there on YouTube
at Living Mana Global on YouTube and uh
such a blessing that we have this
amazing tool
and so it's just one of the things that
you see that we have going on here at
Living Mana so many ways that we are U
being faithful students and so we
servants uh stewards of what God has
entrusted to us and so what we want to
really do is thank you for all your your
gifts for your prayers and for your
offerings that you give to support the
work here at Living mana and one of the
ways you can give is you can go to
Adventist Adventist giving .org and once
you go there you will put in living mana
and then click up in the right hand
corner and what you'll get is a virtual
tithe envelope like you see here and so
what you when you do and you start going
through your tithe envelope you'll see
your tithes and the tithes for living
Mana go to support the northeastern
conference you'll also see our local
church budget where we are able to you
say you were able to support all the
things that we're doing here at Living
Mana you see the the benevolent fund
where we're able to give to the the
needs of so many here at Living mana and
I can tell you firsthand living Mana has
really been a generous hands and feet of
Jesus and helping in every way we can
and we're seeking to be um faithful
stewards of all of God's resources that
he's put into our hands and so we want
to thank you for always uh being willing
to give and to support living mana and
the work that we are doing here and
we're looking forward as we go into the
new year to be h a blessing to as many
as possible and so if you would like to
perhaps uh mail a check to living Mana
you can always mail that check in to PO
Box 428 Owens Crossroads Alabama
35763 and just make sure that you put a
note on the envelope payable to living
Mana online church and we thank you so
much Saints again with all of our heart
uh for for giving to the work of the
Lord and so what we want to do again we
we we always take a moment to thank God
for the offering for all of your gifts
for all your prayers continue to pray
with us as we um do the work that the
Lord has put in our hands could you bow
your heads with us and just pray a
minute for the offering as we thank the
Lord God we do give you praise for this
incredible work for what was once a
dream only a vision Lord we see you are
in it and you have manifest your
goodness and Your Glory thank you for
touching the hearts of your people in
and around the globe everywhere Lord God
thank you for allowing us to be your
hands and feet thank you for allowing us
Lord God not just to be Gatekeepers as
first lady said but we want to share
this manner everywhere and in every way
possible God bless this work we pray
more and more in jesus' name God as we
give you all of the honor give you all
of the glory and all of the praise
father we do not take this work
lightly God we consider it we count it a
high privilege and a high honor to be
able to serve in your Vineyard God thank
you so much in Jesus mighty name amen
[Music]
amen what if I told you you will be
okay that there's nothing in your past
that can't be
forgiven nothing you done no matter how
hurtful or
shameful can stop the power of God's
grace no matter the road you've walked
the places you've
been or the things you've
seen if we confess our sins he is
faithful and righteous to forgive
us to cleanse us from all
unrighteousness
so
today no matter what you're dealing with
no matter what burdens are weighing you
[Music]
down know
this you will be okay
[Music]
[Applause]
are you hurting and broken
within oh overwhelmed by the weight of
your
sin Jesus is
Calling have you come to the end of
yourself do you thirst for a dram from
the
well Jesus is
Calling oh come
to the altar
the father's arms are open myde
forgi was B with the precious blood of
Jesus Christ
[Music]
leave behind your regrets and
mistakes come the day there's no reason
to
wait Jesus is
Calling
bring bring your sorrows and Tra them
for
Joy From the Ashes of new life is
born Jesus is
Calling oh oh come
to the
altar the father's arms are open why
foress was B with the precious blood of
Jesus Christ oh come to
the
altar the father's on the RO wide
foress was B with the Precious Blood of
Jus Christ
[Music]
what isn't he
wonderful sing
Hallelujah Christ is
withow down
before down
before him
for he is Lord of all sing
Hallelujah Christ
[Music]
is sing Hallelujah
[Applause]
Christ for he
is sing
hallelu chist
[Music]
bless
ohe oh precious is
the that makes
me makes me white as soul
[Music]
nothing but nothing but the blood of
Jesus Oh
what is he is he
sing
hallelu CH
is
before for he
[Music]
selu chist
[Applause]
oh what
a oh what
[Applause]
aor sing
H
[Applause]
CHR for he
is for he is
sing
[Music]
hallelu Oh want to
saor
Hallelujah isn't he
wonderful sing
Hallelujah Christ is r
bow down be bow down
before him for he is
Lord sing H sing
Hallelujah Christ
is to
[Music]
the
for was F with the precious blood of
Jesus Christ come
to the
altar
the
unen one
forgi was
with the precious blood of Jesus Christ
[Music]
here at Living Mana we bear each other's
burdens when you need support or prayer
when you're feeling
discouraged or alone or
anxious you don't have to face life
struggles alone
[Music]
let us come boldly unto the throne of
grace that we may obtain mercy and find
Grace to help in our time of
need the Lord is close to the
Brokenhearted and saves those who are
crushed in spirit
[Music]
amen amen one more time greeting Saints
of the most high God uh you know welcome
to uh living man in prayer and praise
time we are back once again amem and I
working kind of overtime today but
praise God we love it we love serving
the lord and we love serving you his
people thank God for you you know today
I I just saw something and I decided you
know what I I want to open up with a
very very special thanks this was our
this is our last production of the year
and you know we we're headed into a new
year but you know what our Tech Team and
our producer sister Patrice our
technicians behind the scene brother
Gavin brother Colin brother Joshua
listen they have done a marvelous job
and we want to give God praise glory and
honor to them you know you never get to
really hear from them but you're seeing
their work when we're out here this is
the fruit of their labor behind the
scene working and pulling it all
together so we just want to praise God
for y'all and tell y'all we love you I
just got a text from Brother Colin you
know what you know what he said he said
to God be the glory amen that we will
Triumph today you know and sister
Patrice said something this morning when
she was praying with us before uh we we
came on the production she said you know
what she was praying about the hiccups
you know here at living man we're not
afraid of the hiccups y'all know what
hiccups are right bumps anomalies
seeming setback turbulence and you know
we always run into stuff but nobody ever
said that the road was going to be easy
no one said it was going to be a smooth
Road God never promised us that but he
did promise US victory at the end if we
hold on he said the race is not given to
the Swift nor the battle to the strong
but to them that endureth to the end
we're here to endure to the end can we
say Amen somebody
amen amen amen sister Jackie my sister
glory to God sister zodwa we see you
there I'm GNA give you a shout out I
know you're in England we always praise
God for you love you so much don't worry
folks I will not be doing a roll call
today okay we already did roll call for
all of y'all we love everybody I would
say like Nicole been saying everybody we
love y'all God bless you
everybody so we're gonna get right into
the praise reports okay well before I
read the praise reports just a reminder
that if you have a prayer request or a
praise report reports please send an
email to pray Living mana. Church we
love to hear your praise and prayers
amen uh if you would like to join a
special ops team or join the prayer team
again send that email to pray Living
mana. Church if you have a request for a
special ops team for one of you yourself
or one of your loved ones please please
send an email to spec ops that's
spops living mana.
church if you would like to join the
women's ministry on Mighty networks
please send an email to women Living
mana. Church and finally if you would
like to join the Men's Ministry please
send an email to seven loaves that's s v
n l o a
VES living Mana . church I'm not sure if
they're going to share those links in
the chat or not but just in case you can
rewind and get those email
addresses praise reports first off I
just want to shout out LM kids who are
turning two years old on January 6th
what a blessing to have this Children's
Program for the last two years Jerry
said they are are going to be
celebrating and partying all month long
and we are going to party along with you
so what a praise to have that awesome
Ministry for our children I just saw
sister blessing welcomed brother Moses
kesan I want to welcome you brother I
didn't see the one in the chat but I saw
your name and I saw our beloved sister
welcome you so welcome to you and and
since I'm doing that before she starts a
praise report there's one special person
I really want to end the year with a
heartfelt grat uh expression of
gratitude and thank you sister Marisella
Johnson I hope you're watching right now
and I know you are because you're always
working in that chat and you're always
praying my beloved sister thank you so
much for the work you do and not just in
English but in Spanish and she's always
in the chat in Spanish she's always
sending up prayer she's always
interceding her and sister Annette Rivas
both who will be singing in just a
moment but sister Marisella we love you
and we are looking forward to you you
already have joined the ranks already
but I know you're coming to be a living
man of prayer Warrior and I want to
thank God that you're officially joining
and I'm looking forward to it but my
sister you do a wonderful job and we um
we love you we praise God for you here
amen all right our first praise report
comes from Laura Powell so this is the
original prayer request hello Church
church family two prayer requests Kelly
will be having surgery to remove a brain
ter tumor beginning at 7:30 California
time and the surgery is expected to last
14 hours the second is for my younger
brother Richard who will be having
extensive shoulder surgery beginning at
12:30 California time thank you for your
prayers and
intercession and the praise report came
thank you so much Saints for continuing
to intercede Kelly's surgery was 20
hours long they didn't finish until 3:30
this morning California time and she's
doing well praising God now for the next
steps in
treatment um and hopefully Laura your
brother Richard is doing well as well so
we will continue to keep his recovery in
prayer uh as well as
Kelly's from Don Cody thank you for
praying about being evicted right away
the paperwork was from another apartment
complex and didn't apply to my current
apartment that is certainly a praise
amen from Ashley Owens I wanted to send
out a praise for all those who have been
praying for me I was able to get an MRI
scheduled for Friday to determine the
reason for my sudden and severe seizures
and other severe neurological symptoms
so thank you all again for your prayers
I hope the sooner the doctor can figure
out the sooner I can treat whatever is
happening amen and we will be keeping
you in prayer Ashley amen from Katie s
praise report for Brent the man I asked
for prayer for last Sabbath he is now
handling his depression better and
according to his family seems to no
longer be suicidal praise God praise God
for that
last but not least Charlotte
stanforth I love this praise report
Sister Charlotte buckle up because she
did a story time amen praise God praise
God especially since my back surgery
I've wondered how God can use me at 83
and shut in careg caregivers coming and
going what can I do as the oldest in
this miracle story I'll be number one
amen enters number two a caregiver who
loves the Lord so of course we talk of
spiritual things but I didn't know about
her concern for her son number two is
probably more than 20 years younger than
I enters number three a n nurse who
checks on me at least two times a week
during the first visit she mentioned
that her 19-year-old daughter had asked
for a Bible number two said she had been
praying for her her son to accept Christ
and he just called her out of the blue
at that point I realized the Holy Spirit
was in our midst mining ministering to
each one of us my little apartment was
being used as a
temple I remembered CS Lewis's book Mere
Christianity and offered it to number
three for her daughter to read while we
were going through a stack of Lewis's
books number three asked if she could
borrow one of his books on Grief that's
when we learned of the tragic deaths of
both her grandmothers and her mother
which led her to becoming a nurse we
listen to more of number two's story of
her son being in the world and now being
woed back to Jesus and the spirit
Comforts The Mother by prompting the son
to call his mother and then number one
me is left with a heart overflowing with
joy at the answer to prayer what can I
do to serve be willing to be used the
story continues with another caregiver
24 years old who loves the Bible but has
very little training who am I to train I
know so little but I've been asked I
have been asking her a lot of questions
about her beliefs and the Sabbath and
the Tabernacle she seemed very
interested so I invited her to watch the
blueprint with me the fulllength version
she watched more when she got home and
journaled seven pages of course we'd
have much time time to talk about about
it since so I have more meaning to not
worrying about what I will say the Holy
Spirit brings whatever to mind God wants
you to say Praise Him Praise Him amen
amen amen Charlotte we love you and what
a blessing you are to so many so thank
you so much for that praise report and
that amazing story amen amen love you
Sister
Charlotte such a so a soldier hanging in
there through it all and we give God
praise for you Saints also we I we
wanted to announce earlier and and seems
that we didn't have to you knew to put
your prayer requests in the chat you can
always put them in there um even when we
pray right now and we get going and
prayer requests are coming up the prayer
warriors are right there in the chat and
they're watching standing by and we're
Gathering all of your prayer requests
and we're continuing to pray even after
today's broadcast so we uh want to
encourage you to uh let us join join in
with you and carrying your burdens to
the Lord and believing that he will hear
and answer and as always we'll come
right here and share it if you share it
with us we'll be more than happy to
share and listen you never know what you
may say and how God may be using your
testimony to set someone else free or to
encourage someone else we hear about it
all the time when you share praise
reports other people are blessed amen by
your story absolutely I mean and and and
your story is his story you are his
vessel and he's using you to be a
blessing not only to bless you but to
bless somebody else so thank God for you
well Saints uh speaking earlier about
hiccups last week we had one of our
beloved prayer warriors on and we had a
hiccup with the sound but this is a wise
warri at right here that we're getting
ready to introduce but because what
she's done today is she sent me all the
prayer requests that she has gathered
and that she's ready to pray through
right now just in case something happens
that was why right but brother Colin
told me earlier today when our text he
said listen we Triumph today we win
today amen and so we're getting ready to
announce uh introduce sister Annette
Rivas who's going to come back and lead
us in intercessory prayer today and we
thank God for her she's a beautiful gift
here does so much work here amongst the
women's ministry and power Wednesday and
with all the graphics and just in
everything she's a a prayer leader
Prayer Ministry leader and we thank God
for sister Annette so bless you as you
come today sister
Annette praise God praise God thank you
thank you so much for having me I'm
hoping I'm being heard I'm not sure if
you guys can hear me but it's such a
privilege to be here with you guys and
um shout out to Sister sha um Sheila and
Sister Pauline that helped me uh with
all of the prayer
requests and so just know brothers and
sisters that if I don't um read out your
prayer um or if you put your prayer
requests um even now uh we have faithful
Warriors that are praying fervently uh
through the chat they're praying live
over the prayer requests and they're
also um collecting them so that we can
later pray on over them throughout the
week uh so just just know that brothers
and sisters you are being prayed
over and with that being said um I'm
going to go ahead and enter into prayer
uh so let us bow our heads and
pray Heavenly Father we praise you and
thank you Lord um for another blessed
Sabbath thank you for this opportunity
of prayer Lord um at this very moment
Lord we come to you with humbled Hearts
asking you Lord to just cleanse us with
the blood of Jesus and make us worthy to
be in your presence at this very moment
Lord Lord uh this morning I want to uh
lift up Esther
she uh put a prayer request she put pray
for my children Jonathan uh Donna and AJ
so that they can get closer to to God
lord and so I'm lifting up this prayer
request um May you just touch their
hearts Lord touch Jonathan Dena and AJ's
hearts Lord may you send your angels to
a camp around them and lead them to you
Lord um whatever means possible that you
can use to attract them to you Lord may
that be done in their life Lord also
want to lift up
EST uh she she put on the prayer chat
please pray for my family we need
spiritual healing and physical healing
and health and she also wants to uh
thank our Lord Jesus Christ for
answering all of her prayers each and
every day what I ask in prayer she she
claims that the Lord has answered so
Praise You Heavenly Father we thank you
for EST lifting up this petition of hers
may you bring um healing to her family
Lord spiritual healing physical healing
um and just bound them to you Lord and
help them Lord in any situation that
they may be in uh we also want to lift
up Paula
McFarland Dr Paula uh she put please
pray for yordi
Gonzalez uh his parents as they as a
family is struggling to stay together
heavenly father I just want to uh ask
Lord that you may be with yordi Gonzalez
and his parents and their family Lord
you know the situation that they are in
asking you to intervene and may you be
the glue that keeps them all together
Lord Lord I also want to pray and lift
up Joy
Mayberry her prayer request is healing
for me and my family and to truly trust
God more Lord you say in your word uh in
psalm
1473 he heals the Brokenhearted and
binds up their wounds Lord and so we're
just lifting and um asking you to just
be with um with joy and and her family
and bring the healing that they're so
desperately asking for and needing um
Lord I also want to lift up Dynasty 80s
um she or they mentioned here in the
prayer uh chat or in the chat please
pray that I am able to find more career
fulfilling find a more career fulfilling
and better paying job please pray for me
to better my credit and be more
financially wise and responsible uh Lord
we just lift up this prayer request
asking you to just step in and and lead
and guide the way for uh for dynasty 80
to find um that career that will be
fulfilling Lord and that um she can they
can find a better paying job especially
in this economy Lord you know the
struggle is real lord um and so uh may
you just bless their walk with you may
you open the doors um that are needing
to be open in order for them to be a
successful heavenly father but
especially successful in you Lord may
you allow them to find a job where they
can make an impact um in their
surroundings on your behalf Lord and may
they just be able to um love their job
and be able to um enjoy going to work
every day Lord and and may you just use
them in any way possible to bring honor
and Glory To Your Name Lord is our
prayer also Lord lifting up Allison um
they put please pray for God's healing
for my family and his Blessing with um
with the house in South Carolina um Lord
and so we're lifting up Alison and her
petition um asking you Lord once again
to bring that healing into her family
where whether that is spiritual physical
mental whatever it may be Lord the
healing needs to come through Lord and
so we're pleading and asking that you
may um just step in and heal Lord each
and every one of those areas that are
needing um healing Lord and and lifting
up this petition for the house in South
Carolina Lord you know exactly what um
Allison is talking about and the plans
that they have laid out um and so Lord
we're just asking Lord that you may step
in and and order order put everything in
order um on their behalf if it's your
will for them to to get that house and
self Carolina May you just open the
doors and and lead the way Lord Lord
we're also praying over um Diane
martinis um she uh they they they put on
the prayer uh chat please pray for my
family to get closer to God in the
following year Lord Lord and so we're
asking Lord that you may please hear The
Cry of Diane and um and her willingness
to to to just ask you Lord to allow them
to grow closer to you especially in
these last days Lord we see the signs of
the times we know that you are um coming
and that you your second coming is so
near Lord and so um attract all of us to
you Heavenly Father help us empty self
of um of ourselves Lord and help us may
you may your Holy Spirit be the one that
feels us and helps us grow Closer to You
Lord and so just be with Diana Martinez
and her whole family and Lord um May you
just send your angels to guard over them
and help them in their daily Walk with
You Lord um May you just allow them to
just grow closer to you every single day
Lord also lifting up Lisa
Marie uh she put in the chat I am in a
hostile work environment now uh
co-workers are lying on me saying I said
things I never said they are making
accus accusatory um and looking to find
fault with me all because I mind my
business Lord and so we're we're lifting
up Lisa Marie and her situation at work
Lord um you tell us that the world um
will come against us when we represent
you just as the world came against you
when you were here Lord and so we're
praying over sister um Lisa Mar asking
Lord that you may take a hold and
control of this situation may you expose
Any Lies may you free her from um these
attacks Lord that she is receiving at
her work Lord and if it is in your will
Lord um that she finds a different job
where she would be at peace and be able
to uh just live her walk with you Lord
without any criticism or any judgment
may you allow that to happen Heavenly
Father we're asking to O for you to open
doors Lord and um and if it's your will
for her to continue at this job Lord may
you remove um that hatred that is coming
against her Lord may you Shield our
sister and help her uh represent you
even even as she is being attacked even
um as they're lying on her Lord we know
that you are a just God and that you
will allow the truth to come forward and
so help our sister just uh help our
sister Lisa Just Hold On Tight to your
promises and trust in you Lord give her
that strength and perseverance that she
is needing um to overcome in this
situation Lord and just take control of
this whole situation uh Lord we're also
lifting up our dear brother Robert Plant
he put in the chat pray for my cousin
Tracy Perry as she has been let go from
her job and denied unemployment benefits
here in um Michigan um
I I'm guessing he is in Michigan to
celebrate her 50th year of life for uh
tomorrow she is turning 50 and to
encourage her through through it all
Lord and so we're lifting up uh Tracy
Lord asking you to just um as I've been
saying before Lord you are a a miracle
working God lord and we know that you
have the ability Lord to just um set our
path straight and and help us through
our journey and so we're asking Lord
that you may be with Tracy and help her
Lord guide her to that perfect job that
is going to be a blessing to her not
only her but her whole family Lord
praising you and thanking you that she
is going to turn 50 tomorrow um May you
allow brother Robert and the whole
family to just have a good time with
Tracy as she is celebrating her 50th
birthday Lord and just uh be with
brother and all of the family give them
traveling Merc mercies Lord and just
continue to lead and guide Tracy um in
this situation Lord may you open the
doors Lord uh that are needing to be
open and may she be able to be to be to
see uh where it is you would have her be
Lord we're pleading the merits of the
blood of Jesus over her and her whole
family please take control of this
situation Lord also lifting up Sarah
Jones um she she put in the chat pray
for my strength for my family for the
past for the passing of my cousin in
Hampton Virginia oh Lord we're just uh
lifting up Sarah and her whole family um
asking you Lord to just send your Holy
Spirit uh to comfort them in this time
of loss Lord asking you to just heal
their hearts and and help them Lord you
know our minds and our hearts and our
our bodies weren't created for morning
Lord and it's it's um it's a difficult
time for us to Pros Lord and so we're
just asking heavenly father that your
Holy Spirit May um just comfort each and
every heart that has been affected by
this loss um and and be with them Lord
as they are grieving the loss of their
cousin and family member um Lord
praising you and thanking you for this
privilege of prayer again Lord I also
want to lift up Katie s um she put in
the chat please pray for my uncle he is
diabetic has CHF and was rushed to the
hospital on Christmas Day due to the um
the pneumonia diagnosis and he is in the
hospital right now on oxygen um Lord and
so we're just pleading uh the merits of
the blood of Jesus over um Katie's Uncle
Lord uh asking Lord that your healing
hand May touch his body and um help him
recover from from this sickness may you
allow Lord um proper oxygen to come into
his love lungs Lord and and and through
his blood Lord and may you just boost up
his immune and allow him Lord to to just
recover from this um from this um ill
diagnosis Lord that they are H that they
have given him Lord and help him be able
to come out of the hospital Lord without
um any assistance may you just heal his
lungs completely Lord and free them um
from any infection is our prayer asking
you also Lord to be with
um with Donna she put in the chat please
pray for me and my son
Jonathan she put too much to mention
Lord but you know Donna Lord and you
know her necessities and and so Lord
we're lifting up this situation um up to
your throne asking you to step in and
intervene on their behalf Lord may you
work everything out um for good for the
wellbeing of Donna and for the
well-being of her son Jonathan Lord
pleading the merits of the blood of
Jesus over them Heavenly Father Lord I
also want to pray over um
vtina as as she put in the chat she has
an unspoken prayer request Lord and so
um I also want to just lift up all of
the unspoken prayer requests Lord you
know each and every one of our hearts
Lord you know our needs Lord so I'm
asking and pleading that you may um
answer each and every one of the
petitions that have been
um that are silent petitions Lord that
you know that are in our hearts in our
minds Lord that we're Desperately
Seeking you for and asking Lord that you
may um step in and answer each and every
one of those petitions according to your
will Lord praising you and thanking you
um in advance for answering Lord even if
the answer is no Lord may you just make
it clear as day may we be able to see
whatever it is that you have um for for
our lives Lord may we accept it and just
allow you Lord to lead and guide because
we know that your plans are higher and
your plans are perfect Lord and so we're
just asking Lord that you may answer
each and every one of those petitions
according to your will praising you and
thanking you Lord also want to lift up
our guest speaker today Lord um our
guest speaker uh Dr Robert uh Lord
asking that you may lead and guide our
our or sorry Dr Roger Schultz asking you
Lord to lead and guide his every word
may you prepare our minds and our hearts
for the message that you have for us
today Lord may you help us not only be
hearers of your word but actually be
doers of what you are asking of us
Heavenly Father help us take those Steps
of Faith in knowing that you are leading
and guiding and um and may every every
seed that is planted today Lord may it
just fall in good fertile soil Lord so
that it can produce much fruit for your
honor and Glory all of this I ask in the
precious name of your son Jesus Christ
amen and
[Music]
amen what a friend we have in Jesus
all our and G
[Music]
to what a
pray it is to
car everything to God in pray
have we trials and
temptations is there
TR
[Music]
anywhere a precious savior he is still
our re
[Music]
you take it to the Lord in
prayer some things we have
not because we
[Applause]
have when we have a
friend who there
when we're weak and heavy
laden CED with the Lord of
care we should never be
discour when
we take it to to the Lord in
prayer some things we have
not because
we when we have a
friend
[Music]
who oh what things we for
oh what need is pain
we oh what peace we are in
[Music]
for oh what need is pain we
oh what peace we of for
[Applause]
[Music]
it oh what need is
pain oh what needs
pain oh what needs pain
[Applause]
[Music]
we we should never be
discouraged when
we take it to the Lord in prayer
[Music]
o take it to the Lord in
prayer Our pray oh
Lord here our
pray oh
Lord knowing that you hear us when we
pray our
PR
Lord here our
pray oh
Lord we know that you are ling and
[Music]
you
e e
Dr rer
all right here we
go all right uh can everyone hear me
now okay um hi I am I'm Roger schwell
and I'm gonna be giving the uh The Talk
today it's really I'm really happy to be
here with you I'm actually here from the
Hilton Hotel in Columbus Ohio at the gyc
conference if you bow your heads with me
we'll begin dear heavenly father thank
you so much for being here and uh be
with us now be with me now as we open
your word and uh open open the the the
Bible and show us uh your wisdom uh as
we as we commence in thy name
amen all right well today I want to talk
to you about something that's been on my
mind uh it is the week after Christmas
it's kind of that interesting time
between Christmas and New
Year's and at this time we've been
talking about you know the birth of
Christ the birth of the Christ child and
so what I wanted to talk about actually
is um just that um this this text that
we have in the Bible called a Behold a
virgin shall conceive now for those of
you who have any kind of a musical
knowledge will know that this text has
been used many times in uh many in many
pieces of music but particularly in one
that is uh dear to my heart which is
handle's
Messiah it's a really interesting uh
talk that we could give about handle's
Messiah we could probably talk a whole
hour about um handle's Messiah I believe
that handle was inspired to write the
words that he did and the music that he
did in fact there's a story about handle
and when he was locked up in his room he
would not come out while he was writing
handle's
messiah in fact there's a story about
one day a servant found him on the
ground after he had written the
Hallelujah Chorus and he said these
words he said I did think I see all
Heaven before me and the great God
himself Seated on his throne with his
company of angels so I do believe that
he was inspired when he wrote this music
um if you go to Westminster Abbey and
see the grave site where he is interred
there in Westminster Abbey there is a um
he actually has this written on the
music that he has there as you can see
it right there and it says I know that
my redeemer liveth and it shows his
faith if if the what we're actually
talking about today is a text from
Isaiah 7:14 it says therefore the Lord
himself shall give you a sign
Behold a virgin shall conceive and bear
a son and shall call his name
Emmanuel now to show you that he was so
into this uh and some of these texts
that he used in handle's Messiah it's
actually very similar and the text that
we have today as seventh day Adventists
he has there written on the music on his
grave I know that my redeemer liveth and
that he shall stand at the latter day
upon the Earth Earth and though worms
destroy this body yet in my flesh shall
I see God a very interesting text uh
from job from the Old Testament to put
in an oratorio about Jesus Christ
himself so let's talk about that let's
talk about this text um because it goes
back to Isaiah which is in the Old
Testament and the text is this again
therefore the Lord himself shall give
you a sign Behold a virgin shall
conceive and bear a son and shall call
his name
Emmanuel you know when the Lord gives a
sign it is because he wants to show you
that he's being serious you know there's
many signs and examples of signs in the
Bible there's one example where instead
of having the sundal go forward certain
degrees it actually went backward that
would be a very hard thing to do right
to make the sun go backward but that's
exactly the sign that was given
to God's people to show them that they
would win that battle uh imagine this
type of a sign imagine a woman giving
birth to a son who is still a virgin
that's going to be biologically
impossible and yet it happened uh and we
see the Fulfillment of that with the
birth of Jesus Christ or I should say
this we see a fulfillment of that in the
birth of Jesus Christ and and you'll see
that that's where we're going today with
this that's in m Matthew 1:22-23 it says
now all this was done that it might be
fulfilled which was spoken of the Lord
by the prophet saying Behold a virgin
shall be with child and shall bring
forth a son and they shall call his name
Emmanuel which is being interpreted God
With Us now it may be of interesting
note that the son that the Virgin Mary
conceived and bore his name was not
Emmanuel so there is a meaning here his
name was actually Jesus as we know and
she was instructed to call him Jesus but
here the the sign is Emanuel and when
you see a discrepancy like this this
should make you study harder that maybe
there's something else beneath the
surface and that's what we're going to
talk about
today so first of all let's decide and
let's make sure that we're clear on
exactly what happened there this is from
Robert Shaw something that was written
back in the 1700s when Han's Messiah was
written and this is from the reformed
Faith an exposition of the Westminster
Confession of faith in chapter 7 what
they're going over here is exactly what
it was that we as Christians believe
happened when the Holy Spirit came into
the Virgin Mary it says here quote the
human nature of Christ was conceived by
the power of the Holy Ghost In the Womb
of the Virgin Mary and was formed of of
her substance the body of Christ was not
created out of nothing neither did it
descend from heaven but it was formed by
the agency of the Holy Spirit of the
substance of the Virgin hence Mary is
called the mother of Jesus and he is
called the fruit of her womb and the
seed of the woman folks this is really
important to understand you know there's
some people that just simply can't
accept the fact that the Plan of
Salvation of God the Father God the son
and God the holy Spirit when it was
conceived in heaven would include
anything that would have to do with
human or humans or the substance of
humans but this clearly
shows that at least one of the major
foundations of the Plan of Salvation
which is the Incarnate Jesus Christ
actually depended on human flesh and in
this case it was the Virgin Mary it
wasn't that Jesus just came down from
heaven it was that he was born of a
virgin and this is something that often
times we sometimes ignore or forget
about because so much is made of the
Virgin Mary that we don't think about it
some of our brothers and sisters in
other denominations will think that the
Virgin Mary was something special uh she
was something special but she was not
sinless she it's not she's not someone
that we pray to or that's someone that
is alive currently in heaven she was a
human being just like us she sinned just
like us but yet she was upright and she
was was chosen by God to whom the Jesus
Christ the Savior would come through and
into this
world so let's keep that in mind as we
go on what's even more interesting is
when we look at the genealogy of Jesus
as you can see here on the top portion
of this slide on the right is we have
the genealogy of
Mary and on the bottom portion we have
the genealogy of Jesus now Luke was a
physician and he looked at things
biologically and that's why we have in
Luke 3: 23-38 we have the genealogy of
Mary let's take a look at that since
we're talking about the Virgin Mary and
what you'll notice going back is we have
a number of people in her ancestry that
were let's just say colorful figures for
instance Boaz Boaz as you may recall
married Ruth and Ruth was a
moabit now where did the moabites come
from the moabites came from the
ancestral relationship between lot and
his eldest daughter that is something
that is well documented and so realize
that that is a uh an interesting aspect
to the genealogy of Mary and therefore
Jesus uh remember that Boaz married um
uh Ruth was married to Boaz but boaz's
mother and father was sammon and Rahab
in her genealogy line so think about
that that that Rahab who was The
Prostitute living in Jericho yeah but
yet accepted the two spies and kept them
and saved them and allowed them and had
respect and fear for the Israelites
Rahab who W used to be a prostitute
became an upright woman and married uh
salmon and gave birth to Boaz uh through
the genealogy of Jesus Christ as you can
see there again another colorful
ancestor if we go back even further we
can go to Perez and Perez was one of the
twins that was born of Tamer and as you
recall Tamar went through many of the
sons of Judah uh until there was nothing
left for her there was no inheritance
for her and she tricked Judah into
sleeping with her and the product of
that was Perez who is an ancestor of
Mary and therefore Jesus Christ uh we
can go all the way back to Abraham
remember that Abraham was promised many
many children and he was going to do
this through Sarah the promised uh wife
but um it wasn't happening and so even
before the age of 90 Sarah had an idea
that maybe this would come about through
her handmaiden Hagar and instead of
Abraham practicing righteousness by
faith he tried to do things on his own
accord and uh through Hagar the Bond
woman as it talks about Paul um in in
the New Testament uh there
was uh the ishmail which was not to be
the ancestor of Jesus Christ and so what
we see here is we see a number of
Unfaithful activities Unfaithful women
let's say that finally eventually led to
the Virgin Mary who would give birth to
Jesus Christ um let's go on to
Revelation 12 because this becomes an
interesting aspect uh if we read
Revelation 12 we see at the very
beginning of that chapter a woman who is
pregnant just like the Virgin Mary was
and there are two parts to Revelation CH
12 there is the first part which we'll
read uh a verse out of and then there is
the second part and what I want you to
do is think about who this woman is who
does she represent based on the
description in Revelation
12 so in verse 5 it says and she brought
forth a Manchild who was to rule all
nations with a rod of iron and her child
was caught up on God and to his throne
who is that that woman that's giving
birth to this man who will rule All
Nations well clearly they're talking
about Jesus Christ and the mother of
Jesus Christ is Mary so there seems to
be an illusion in the beginning of this
chapter to Mary being the woman but as
we see clearly as we go on
uh this is a an illusion to another
woman at the end of the chapter because
it says here that the dragon was wroth
with this woman and went to make war
with the remnant of her seed which keep
the Commandments of God and have the
testimony of Jesus Christ here clearly
this woman is the church so let's take a
look at this again uh because what we
see here is an interesting dichotomy
which is brought up in fact it's not a
dichotomy it's a similarity because in
both situations what we have is we have
a woman who with the help of the Holy
Spirit it gives rise to a Manchild who
keeps the Commandments of God and has
the faith of Jesus Christ okay the
testimony of Jesus Christ which is the
spirit of Prophecy uh and in the second
case we also have the remnant of her
seed so in other words this is a
continuation of that same equation this
is the same seed that was there before
and again we have something where we
have an equation where we have the Holy
Spirit that's coming into the church at
the last days and there will also be
just as there was an offspring in the
first equation there will be an
offspring in the second equation and the
result will
be those that keep the Commandments of
God and have the testimony of Jesus
Christ I'm talking of course about the
144,000 so you might say how is it
possible that the church at the end will
be a chased virgin given all of the
escapades that she has been through all
the unfaithfulness that the Bible and
history has documented in its past may I
remind you that in second Corinthians
112 it says for I am jealous over you
with a Godly jealousy this is Paul
talking to the church for I have
espoused you to one husband that I may
present present you as a chased virgin
to Christ in other words Paul is waiting
for that day that he may present the
church as a chased virgin for marriage
to Jesus Christ so here is the equation
that I want you to think about at this
time of year when we celebrate the
Christ child we know that the Holy
Spirit
Plus adulterous women in the past that
finally give rise to a chased virgin in
the form of the Virgin Mary will
equal Jesus Christ someone who kept all
of The
Commandments but had the faith of Jesus
Christ if we look at that same equation
we will see it repeating itself Jesus
Christ who was the the the the antitype
of many types in the Old Testament is
himself a type of something that will be
in the end times and that will be the
holy Spirit or the pouring out of the
latter rain on the church who used to be
an adulterous woman who used to be
unfaithful who was not pure and yet Paul
as he says in 2 Corinthians will present
it to Christ as a chased virgin folks
what can be the
only equation that this will be equal to
it will be equal to the 144,000 as we'
have seen in Revelation 12
so how can I say that how is it possible
that we can do that and what does it
mean let's investigate there are many
similarities in the Bible very specific
peculiar similarities between Jesus
Christ and the 144,000 as we've just
said Jesus Christ was conceived by the
Holy Spirit and we know the 144,000 at
the end will also be conceived by the
holy spirit in form of the latter Reign
Jesus Christ was born of a virgin whose
ancestors were sinful women the 144,000
will also be born of a virgin whose
ancestors were sinful women or
churches Jesus Christ has the nature of
Adam after the fall yet he never sins he
would rather die than sin folks 144,000
has the nature of Adam after the fall
yet they never sin they would rather die
than
sin Jesus Christ had the Elijah message
preached before his ministry so did the
144,000 Jesus Christ keeps the
Commandments of God and has the
testimony of Jesus Christ the 144,000
also Jesus Christ had religious leaders
which used civil Roman authority to
persecute him and his followers because
he refused to follow their teachings so
too will the 144,000 have religious
leaders use civil authority to persecute
because they refused to follow their
teachings Jesus Christ
bore his cross and died refused to drink
the vinegar Pro provided by the Roman
soldier at the end the 144,000 also will
bear their cross and die to self refus
to drink the wine offered by Rome Jesus
Christ after the day in the day of
atonement must stand in the presence of
God the Father without an intercessor on
the power of only the holy spirit so too
will the 144,000 must stand in the
presence of God without an intercessor
on the power of the Holy Spirit Jesus
Christ is the represents and is the
first fruits as mentioned in 1
Corinthians
15:20 well in Revelation
14:4 the 144,000 are the first fruits
and they follow Christ wherever he goes
Jesus Christ ascends to heaven to
continue the ministry in the Heavenly
Temple we know from early writings that
the 144,000 Ascend to heaven and
continue the ministry in the Heavenly
Temple but there's more Jesus Christ it
says in sec in 1 Peter 222 and in Isaiah
539 will have no guile found in his
mouth the same exact thing is said of
the 144,000 in Revelation
145 Jesus Christ was sealed sorry Jesus
Christ there was no fault found in him
that is found in Luke 234 and 14 and
John 8 1838 it's also found of the
144,000 in Revelation
145 Jesus Christ was sealed by his
father and it is mentioned there in John
verse John chapter 6 verse 27 the same
exact thing is said about the 144,000
found in Revelation
7:4 folks if we look at the writings of
the spirit of Prophecy of Ellen White
she says that the Angels wanted to
deliver him
the Angels wanted to deliver Jesus but
the commanding angels suffered it not
this is in early writings page
170 she says exactly the same thing in
early writings 272 of the 144,000 that
Angels wanted to deliver the Saints but
a tall commanding Angel suffers them not
to do it folks in Luke
2243 of Jesus Christ it says that an
angel comes from Heaven to strengthen
Christ to make the sacrifice in great
controversy page 611 to 613 the angel of
Revelation 18 will give strength to the
remnant to endure the time of trouble
finally Jesus Christ makes the great
demonstration of God's character of love
and vindicates his law so too will the
144,000 who are the first fruits will
finally demonstrate and vindicate God's
character of his love folks all of these
are not just by coincidence
the same equation leads to the same
product and those products should have
parallels and in fact they do and it's
not by coincidence God is trying to show
us that where God intervene on man's
behalf using humans he will do the same
again just as he used the womb of the
Virgin Mary to facilitate the Plan of
Salvation there is going to be a usage
of an extraordinary use of humans in the
last days to vindicate God's character
and his love so once again the Holy
Spirit Plus a chased virgin equals Jesus
even though those chased V that chased
virgin came from sinful women so too
once again the Holy Spirit Plus a Chase
virgin at the end will give rise to the
144,000 even though that chased virgin
who is the church will have an
adulterous history we can can be
reassured that Christ has everything
under
control again the sign therefore for the
Lord himself shall give you a sign
Behold a virgin shall conceive and bear
a son and shall call his name
Emmanuel interesting now that we read it
again because you can see that this is a
dual fulfillment sign not only is this a
sign to show that Jesus Christ will be
born as fulfilled in Matthew 1:22 and 23
but it's also a sign that there will be
a son a
Manchild from the remnant of her seed
that will make fulfillment of Revelation
12 and that 144,000 will also be God
with
us so I believe that this analogy that
shows that the baby is the 144,000 and
this baby that comes from a woman is
emblematic
of much of the Bible if there's one
theme that repeats itself over and over
again in the Bible it is this theme of a
woman not being able to have a child we
see that with
Sarah we see it with Hannah we see it
with Rachel we see it with the woman uh
in Israel we see this over and over and
over again and I believe that the
stories of the Bible that show this type
of theme are trying to tell us yes we
know that your church the church that
you belong to has not yet been able to
have the child the
144,000 but as difficult as it was for
these women to have a baby and yet they
did so too will happen again with the
church in the last days it will have a
baby let's take a look at what we're
talking about here here you see Sarah in
her 90s almost in her 90s laughing you
remember this story this is the story
where Abraham was sitting outside and he
was visited by three visitors and one of
them told Abraham and Sarah overheard
that this time next year Sarah would be
with a child and she laughed let's
unpack this a little bit and see what
this means now knowing that the child is
representative of the 144,000 and the
mother the church so here we have both
Sarah and Abraham who are entertaining
three guests no not just three guests
but Three Angels in other words folks
they are listening to The Three Angels
messages I want you to think about that
and what are the three Angels messages
as recall the first Angel's message is
that give glory to God fair and give
glory to God because the hour of his
judgment has
come remember Jesus who was the first
angel of these three came to Abraham and
told him Abraham in terms of Sodom and
Gomorrah the hour of my judgment has
come and then they started to bargain
and what happened to the second and the
third Angel remember what the second and
third Angel's messages are in Revelation
they say that Babylon Babylon has fallen
has fallen that great city which made
all nations drink of the right of the
wine of the wrath of her of his fornica
her fornication
and then the third Angel is basically if
Babylon has fallen you need to get out
what do those two angels the second and
third Angel do when they go on to visit
lot in Sodom and Gomorrah they say lot
this city is going down and you need to
get out these folks are the exactly the
same Angels messages being given to
Sarah and Abraham as the Three Angels
messages are being given to our church
our church is Sarah we are well over 90
years old and there's no way that we're
going to have it looks a child but yet
God is saying you will and what does
Sarah do when she hears this message
folks we heard this message this message
that I'm talking about is not a new
message we heard this message in 1888 it
was the message of righteousness by
faith and what does that mean
righteousness by faith is not
righteousness because we are going to do
a good work our works are our good works
are like filthy rags and yes if it
depended on that and we looked at our
church it would be impossible for us to
have a child no the message is of
righteousness by faith in fact Ellen
White said that indeed I've been asked
whether or not the third Angel's message
is justification by faith and she says
indeed it is and so this message has
been given to us as a as a church and
what did we do when we heard this
message in 1888
we essentially laughed we thought it
could not happen we didn't agree with it
we thought we had just discovered the
Ten Commandments and we believe that if
we could keep the Ten Commandments like
the israels like the children of Israel
thought they could at sin that somehow
we would be able to be worthy of having
righteousness no keeping the Ten
Commandments is important as you recall
it's one of the characteristics of the
144,000 but it is not by concentrating
on the Ten Commandments as Ellen White
has said the Ten Commandments have no
power to save you they simply tell you
like a mayor does in the morning that
you don't look good you've got to go and
make yourself look good first how do you
do that the only way this can happen is
righteousness by faith and that is what
the message was when we were confronted
back in 1888 at the fact that we had
rejected that message what did the
church say what did we do we denied that
we had rejected that message and so who
did Sarah reject the fact that she had
laughed I didn't laugh she said We are
following history so well but folks if
Mary sorry if Sarah represents the
church in this situation then that must
mean
that Isaac represents the 144,000 let's
take a look and see if that is the case
remember what happened to Isaac it says
that the 144,000 would follow the lamb
wherever he went folks Isaac followed
Abraham wherever he
went and remember what happened Isaac
was taken to an altar and he was almost
sacrificed in fact the blade came down
and almost pierced him before an angel
told Abraham to stop in other words
Isaac almost died but
didn't folks that's exactly what we know
will happen to the 144,000 in the end
there will be persecution so bad in yet
not a single hair on our heads after the
close of probation will be affected it
will look as though the blade will come
down and almost kill us but just at the
last moment before it does so it will
stop and as you recall Abraham looks up
and he sees the substitute in the
thicket and that substitute is instead
sacrificed folks remember at the end
when it looks as though there is no hope
yet we will look up and we will will see
our substitute coming in the clouds to
save us and so yes in fact Isaac
fulfills the parallel with the
144,000 we see another example of this
in the Bible we see in First Kings when
Solomon is asking to be given wisdom
remember Jesus Christ comes to him in
vision and he's there before the Ark of
the Covenant he's in the most holy place
in Vision essentially
and Christ comes to him and
says what is it that you want tell me
anything and I'll give it to you and
instead of asking for riches he asks for
wisdom so that he can judge his people
now stop there and think about this for
anyone who understands the sanctuary
message this should be huge because here
we have the son of
David another name for the son of David
is Jesus here we have the son of David
standing before the Ark of the Covenant
and we know that this is a a sign of the
investigative judgment and he's asking
God for wisdom to judge his people folks
this is a sign that what is going on
here and next is going to be emblematic
of what's Happening after
1844 and what happens right after that
we see that there are two prostitutes
who are living Under One Roof who both
claim a single baby which one is the
true mother
Solomon can't
tell there's they look identical and if
we look at this from the Viewpoint of
the baby and what does the baby
represent yes the baby represents the
144,000 we have a sword that's coming
down on the
baby it's about to cut the baby in half
but it
stopped and we often ask ourselves this
is actually very similar to Isaac as you
can see we often ask ourselves why does
the 144,000 have to go through such
perilous times at the end what is the
purpose of this and here we can see
clearly that the purpose of this is to
show the universe and all of the courts
men that are watching that Solomon's
judgment is true and that's what it says
immediately after it says that the that
the son of David and everyone wondered
after the son of David how he was so
smart and how he could judge so well and
that's exactly the same thing we'll come
back to this theme the purpose of the
144,000 is to vindicate to the universe
that God's judgment is correct let me
just stop there for a second and inform
you that it wasn't until Jesus died on
the cross that the entire universe
finally understood in full that Satan
was wrong that's a pretty tough crowd I
mean the flood Israel the prophets there
were still some in the universe that
thought
perhaps Lucifer was correct but it
wasn't until Lucifer murdered the Son of
God on the cross that that was the key
to understanding so the question is is
why are we still here it's not because
the universe is in doubt about Lucifer
no the universe is in doubt about us we
the way we behave on this planet not
just to our enemies but even to our
friends people even in our own families
the sin that we do the recurrence that
we do the universe is not convinced that
that the power of God has the ability to
save us to bring us to heaven and to not
regenerate sin again and you can't blame
them I mean look at what happens even on
our own
church so that is the question how is it
that God is going to show the
universe that we are safe to save and if
we go back to Solomon you will see that
the only way that they could tell the
difference between the two women was
with the sword it was the sword that had
to almost come down on the baby that
would show the difference between the
true mother and the false mother and we
know what the sword represents it
represents the word of God it is the
word of God that will show the
difference the whole world between one
prostitute and the other prostitute and
there's good news folks because even
though the real mother is a prostitute
as Paul says one day she will be a
chased virgin and that is what will
happen
so if that is the case if it is
true that there will be a baby and a
delivery we should see something about
this in the Bible and in the spirit of
Prophecy and I want to show you that
there are actually three phases to a
Jewish wedding there is a covenant a
consummation and then a celebration
which usually lasts about seven days now
what I want to show you here is what
Ellen G white talks about when Christ
throws down the censor in the most holy
place at the time of the end when he's
done judging the living and he's about
ready to come back to this planet and
that in initiates the falling of the
seven last plagues let's take a look and
see what she says in terms of the
consummation she says of that time this
is an early writings page 279 every case
had been decided for life or death while
Jesus had been ministering in the
sanctuary the Judgment had been going on
for the righteous dead and then for the
righteous living Christ had received his
kingdom having made the atonement for
his people and blotted out their sins
the subjects of the Kingdom were made up
the marriage of the Lamb consummated and
we can see it there that right at that
moment when he drops the sensor right
there when the actual close of probation
occurs finishes the consummation of the
holy spirit with the chased virgin known
as the church and now we are right in
Revelation 12 with a woman lighted up by
the sun on the moon standing on the moon
and she is pregnant now if she's
pregnant she has to deliver that baby
and the delivery happens next that means
the delivery of that baby which is
144,000 should happen after the close of
probation during the falling of the
seven last plagues let's see what
happens in terms of
that let's go to Isaiah 66 6-10 and
14-5 this is Isaiah
okay a voice of noise from the city a
voice from the temple folks we know what
voice this is this is the voice of
Christ saying it is finished throwing
down the temp throwing down the censor
and the close of probation everything is
made up a voice of the Lord that render
recompense to his enemies now listen to
what Isaiah says here before she
travailed that means goes into labor she
brought forth before her pain came she
was delivered of a Manchild here's
exactly what's going on during the time
of the falling of the seven last plagues
when everyone is
sealed the mother of us all the woman
the church Revelation CH 12 the remnant
of her seed is going to give birth to
the
144,000 but it usually takes nine months
you might add to go from consummation to
birth no this is going to happen
immediately and we have proof here in
Isaiah 66
they say in verse 8 who hath heard such
a thing who hath seen such things shall
the Earth be made to bring forth in one
day or shall a nation be born at once
for as soon as Zion travailed she
brought forth her children as I shall I
bring to the birth and not cause to
bring forth here Isaiah is is channeling
the Holy Spirit as he's writing and what
he's saying here is that God is saying I
am going to bring to fruit the 144,000
it's going to happen just as I've
explained
it this this idea of travailing is seen
all throughout the Bible and let me
suggest to you that whenever it talks
about a woman in travail it's talking
about the time after the close of
probation during the seven last plagues
let's take a look here this is Isaiah 26
like as a woman with child that draw
near the time of her delivery is in pain
and crith out in her pangs so have we
been in thy sight oh Lord we have been
with child we have been in pain we have
as it were brought forth wind we have
not wrought any Deliverance in the earth
neither have the inhabitants of the
world
fallen so now what happens the dead men
shall live together with my dead body
shall they arise awake and sing ye that
dwell in the dust for thy du is as the
DW of herbs and the Earth shall cast out
the dead here you can clearly see that
the travailing of this woman is
associated with the second coming of
Jesus Christ come out my people enter
into thy Chambers and shut thy doors
about thee hide thyself as it were for a
little moment until the indignation be
overpassed I believe it's talking about
the seven last
plagues so again there is a
consummation of the holy spirit with the
chased virgin there is the birth of
144,000 and from that is the travail but
there's more evidence all throughout
this is Jeremiah 31-9 you know that that
time of trouble when the seven last
plagues fall is known as Jacob's time of
trouble well here we have see it very
plainly in Jeremiah chapter 30 it says
ask ye now and see whether a man doth
travail with child wherefore do I see
every man with his hands on his loins as
a woman in travail and all the faces are
turned turn into paleness alas for that
day is great so that none is like it it
is even the time of Jacob's trouble but
he shall be saved out of
it folks it's amazing we even have it in
the New Testament so this is Paul in his
letter to the Thessalonians chapter 5: 1
to 11 he's talking about what's going to
happen at the end peace and safety have
you heard that does that sound familiar
peace and safety then sudden destruction
cometh upon them as travail upon a woman
with child and they shall not
Escape he goes on in verse n for God
hath not appointed us to wrath but to
obain Salvation by our Lord Jesus Christ
who died for us that whether we wake or
sleep we should live together with him
wherefore Comfort yourselves together
and edify one another even also ye
do
again let's review we have seen at this
time of year the birth of the Christ
child with the Virgin Mary as his mother
a human element but as his father the
Holy Spirit folks that is a type of what
is going to happen again in the future
except on a much larger scale we are
going to see a chased virgin but she is
going to be the purified church at the
end which comes from a long line of
women that have been unfaithful up to
that point just as Mary came from a long
line of Unfaithful women however in both
cases the holy spirit will come into
them and the result of that will be what
we see in the first part of Revelation
CH 12 which is Jesus Christ and also the
144,000 which we see in the second part
of re Revelation 12 and we've gone
already over how they are very similar
well that travail or that birthing is
going to happen and let's see what Jesus
himself has to say about it this is in
the 16th chapter of John now John is
talking to his disciples and notice what
he says he says now Jesus knew that they
were desirous of asking him and he said
unto them do ye inquire among yourselves
of what I said a little while and you
shall see me and you shall not see me
and then again a while and you shall see
me so what's going on here Jesus is
talking about the time of the end that's
the part that you have to understand he
says verily verily I say unto you that
ye shall weep and lament but the world
shall rejoice and ye shall be sorrowful
but your sorrow shall be turned to Joy
let me explain the first analogy that
Jesus uses as what you guessed it a
woman in travail verse 21 a woman when
she is in travail hath sorrow because
her hour is come but as soon as she is
delivered of the child she remember no
more the anguish for the joy that a man
is Born Into the world couple of points
here notice he uses the term hour is
come that's very prophetic and talks
about the delivery of the child and no
more in anguish this is exactly going to
be the experience of the church at the
very end notice here he says that a man
is Born Into the world it's correct for
him to say that if he's referring to the
144,000 because in Revelation the
144,000 are all men now I don't think
that the 144,000 actually at the end of
time will be just men but prophetically
this is what we're talking about because
it's a man child and it has to be in
parallel with Jesus because Jesus was a
man so go along with
it John goes on and ye now therefore
have sorrow but I will see you again and
your heart shall rejoice and your joy no
man taketh away from you and in that Day
verse 23 now when he's talking about in
that day what is he referring to he's
referring to the day where the woman is
travailing above again and in that day
you shall ask me nothing verily verily I
say unto you whatsoever ye shall ask the
father in my name he will give it to you
he goes on hitherto you've asked nothing
in my name ask and you shall receive
that in your joy may be full these
things have I spoken unto you in
Proverbs but the time cometh when I
shall speak no more unto Proverbs but I
shall show you plainly of the father
verse 26 in that day again which day are
we talking about we're talking about
that day when a woman is in travail and
when do we say say that was that was
after the close of probation when
everybody is sealed and the Seven
plagues are falling question for you is
it our understanding that Jesus is still
in the most holy place interceding on
our behalf the answer is no he has
already dropped the sensor he has left
the most holy place he doesn't need to
be there anymore and the reason is is
because there's no more sin now why is
there no more sin well it is because
God's sealed people are right
and why are they righteous is it because
they've worked on things is it because
they've done the right things they have
they follow the Commandments of God but
not because they in they they were
working on that particularly the reason
why is because of righteousness by faith
faith is the key now if you remember the
seal at the ends those that are sealed
away from God are sealed in the forehead
and in the hand in other words it
doesn't matter
if you decide to do against God or just
do against God it's the same thing but
notice that those that are sealed the
144,000 that are sealed are only sealed
in the foreheads they are not sealed in
the hand we don't care about the hand
because our doings are like filthy rags
the way to us to be righteous is to
understand and have faith and that's
where it must start this is the reason
why it's not good to be going around
telling people what to do because even
even if they comply with what you're
saying they're just getting a seal in
the hand what we ought to be doing is
showing them the word of God and let the
Holy Spirit work on them then they will
get the seal in their head that is where
the decisions need to be made so we've
just shown that because we have true
righteousness by faith that they will be
righteous and if they are righteous they
will no longer be sinning and if they're
no longer going to be sinning after the
close of
probation there's no need to have an
inter in the most holy Place let's see
if that is the case let's see if Jesus
agrees with that Viewpoint verse 26
again we pick it up and in that day
which day is that again that's the day
of Labor that she was that he was
talking about before that's after the
close of probation in that day ye shall
ask in my name and I say
not did you see that word not I say not
unto you that I will pray the father for
you wow what did he just say here he's
saying in that day where that woman is
travailing I'm not going to be praying
the father for you I'm not going to be
ministering on your behalf I'm not going
to be a high priest in the most holy
Place well why let's hear what Jesus has
to say why will he not be doing it verse
27 for the father himself loveth you now
why does why does God the Father love
you because he sees Jesus he doesn't see
us he sees Jesus because Jesus has
covered us and what does it do with us
because ye have loved me and have what's
the word
believed what's another word for believe
Faith righteousness by faith that I have
come out from God I come forth from the
father and I am come into the world
again I leave the world and go to the
father folks this is so important to
understand when you start to understand
what's happening at the
end and when you understand the Virgin
and you understand the Holy Spirit and
you understand that there's going to be
another birth and you understand that
there's going to be a travail now this
comes into play and you can understand
the Theology of what is going on at this
point because you understand what these
analogies mean and I just have to stop
there and just say how amazing it is
that God the father and God the son have
put together a way of explaining the
plan of Sal The Plan of Salvation in a
way that is so plain and is so easy to
understand because it is something that
we all can understand all of us were
born of a
woman all of us there's not a single
person here that was not born of a woman
we understand what how women get
pregnant we understand how they give
birth and what happens during during
birth and this is exactly what is about
to happen at the
end so you can see that there is going
to be a travail now we talked about this
before we said how it's POS how is it
possible that this could happen it's so
improbable our church is too old our
church is not a chased virgin and yet
look what was the type of this the type
was that Sarah was 90 years old and she
could not have a baby it got even worse
we had a virgin who got pregnant and
gave a baby look there's nothing that's
going to be easy about this God knows
this and that's why he's given us so
many examples let's do another example
real quick what about Hannah Hannah is
the church Hannah was married to a
husband who had another wife that had
many many children is and she and she
persecuted Hannah is there another
church that claims to have many children
that persecutes absolutely Hannah was so
insisted on wanting to have a
baby that she went to the high priest
and was praying the high priest thought
she was drunk and he said these words
when are you going to stop drinking the
wine as if to say to us today the church
who is the woman who wants a child you
will get that child when you stop
drinking the wine of Babylon that's when
you will get the child she prayed she
did have the child and that boy's name
was Samuel does he
fit does he fit the parall of the
144,000 yes he does we know from early
writings that ell G white when she was
in Vision Christ was walking in heaven
and they came to the temple and he says
wait only the 144,000 go into the temple
in other words the 144,000 will spend
the rest of Eternity ministering in the
temple this is what she says in early
writings and what did Samuel do after
Samuel was old enough after Samuel was
delivered and brought up at
home finally the day came when it was
time to go to the temple and Samuel just
like the 144,000 will serve in the
temple for the rest of his life you can
see these parallels over and over
again we see this again in terms of the
woman we see it here the woman Mary Mary
of Bethany who was also Mary Magdalene
who was also the woman caught in the act
who was also the woman who washed
Jesus's feet with her hair and her tears
you remember at Simon's Feast let's go
back here is the woman caught in the act
of adultery Jesus says to her the woman
who is the church where are your
accusers didn't even one of them come to
condemn you no Lord she said and Jesus
says neither do I go and sin no more
this is one of the characteristics of
the 144,000 they keep the Commandments
of God this is John
8:10 there's very good evidence to
believe that this same woman followed
Jesus and was Mary of Bethany the one
that sat at Jesus's feet the one that
was there and present at Simon's feast
and we see her again in another
beautiful
picture and she's washing the feet of
Jesus remember remember the uh the
parable that Jesus gave to Simon he says
Simon I want to tell you something he
says there was two people that owed
money one owed 500 and one owed 50 and
they were both forgiven which one is
going to love the master more and Simon
chose correctly he said the 500 because
he owed more and this is what Jesus was
showing the difference between Simon who
just welcomed Jesus in and did not even
welcome him with a
kiss and Mary who was sitting at his
feet this is righteousness by faith is
truly understanding the situation that
we're in and that Jesus Christ
physically saves us from stoning and
that he also makes us clean and sees
through all of the dirty laundry that we
have you can see here that the church
who's represented by Mary is washing
Jesus's feet with her hair what does the
bible tell us about a woman's hair 1
Corinthians 11:14 does not the very
nature of things teach you that if a man
has long hair it is a disgrace to him
but if a woman has long hair it is her
glory for for long hair is given to her
as a covering do you see this she is
using her covering her glory which she
can never make grow faster she cannot
work to grow her hair her hair is simply
something that grows naturally given and
imbued by God so too is the glory of the
church at the end will be given by God
it says in Ephesians 3:21 unto him be
glory in the church by who by Jesus
Christ throughout all ages World Without
End a
amen the hair of Mary is like the
gloriousness and the righteousness of
the church it's not something that she
worked on it's something that she will
be given and she will use that glory to
glorify God In The End by vindicating
that his judgment is correct and what
after this episode happens did Jesus say
to Mary he said in Luke
750 thy faith has saved thee Go In Peace
So no notice the two characteristics
that this woman gets from Jesus number
one she sins no more and number two it's
the faith that actually saves her those
are the very two characteristics that we
see in the 144,000 they keep the
Commandments of God and have the faith
of Jesus Christ and which one of those
two is going to save them it is
righteousness by faith the keeping of
The Commandments is a natural occurrence
when you have righteousness which occurs
by faith which happens from Grace from
God folks this is such a deep
thought again the Holy Spirit Plus
adulterous woman leading to a chased
virgin will lead to Jesus Christ we know
that just as powerful as we know that
and just as much as we know that that is
the case and is a doctrine of the church
from many many years ago so too in the
future the Holy Spirit Plus yes
adulterous woman in the past will give R
to a chased virgin as Paul writes and
this will lead to the
144,000 folks again why is it that this
is going to be the case it's going to be
the case because Jesus Christ judgment
needs to be shown to the universe just
as Solomon was shown to be a good judge
after the incident of the two women so
too will Jesus need to be Vindicated in
his Judgment of the the universe in
front of the universe and we have a part
to play because we have a potential role
in being on the 144,000 how is that
possible well there is levitical law
that goes back that anything that was
made a first portion of that was given
to God known as the first
fruits we have already shown how both
Jesus and the 144,000 were the first
fruits and so what is the law regarding
this what is the purpose of having the
first fruits again as we said the
144,000 are going to be walking this
planet they are going to be the worst
generation in terms of genetics they're
going to be living in the worst times of
Earth history and God is going to take
the worst of the worst as he loves to do
and he's going to show them to be
perfect not based on their own works but
based on righteousness by faith he is
going to do this for
them and when the universe sees
this product of this birth they are
going to know that everything else
everything else that has been saved the
righteous dead that are still in the
grave are safe to save and where do we
know that from we know that from a text
in Romans
11:16 this is where Paul says for if the
first fruit is Holy the lump is also
holy and if the root is Holy so are the
branches folks is it is isn't it
wonderful that we can serve a God who
wants to be so intimate with us that we
are
actually so integral in his Plan of
Salvation for the entire universe we
have a role to play and if we understand
what he has done for us and our role to
play that righteousness will come by
faith let's bow our heads dear heavenly
father thank you so
much for making the Plan of Salvation so
clear to us in such simple terms that we
can understand and find evidence for in
the Bible please give us this uh please
give us this this uh wisdom this
understanding that once we have faith we
might get righteousness from that faith
in thy name amen
thank you for joining us today if this
is your first time worshiping with us
please check out our website at Living
mana. Church we are not just here for
Sabbath service we have weekly
programming too that covers mental
health physical health weekly prayer
service Financial Health and proving the
existence of God it is our desire that
our programming will continue to bless
bless you please continue to pray for us
as we fulfill God's mission to go into
all the world with the Gospel of Jesus
Christ
[Music]
a for